<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves from Malta written by a gentleman of that iland, to a friend of his in Fraunce. Shewing the desperate assault and surprising of two castles of the Turkes, by the Italians forces, vpon the eight day of September last past. Translated according to the Italian copie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125021</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898539</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173301</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173301)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2033:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves from Malta written by a gentleman of that iland, to a friend of his in Fraunce. Shewing the desperate assault and surprising of two castles of the Turkes, by the Italians forces, vpon the eight day of September last past. Translated according to the Italian copie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3, [1]; [88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Thomas Creede, for Iohn Hippon, and are to be sold at his shop in Watling-streete, adioyning to the Red Lyon Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno. 1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title from A2r second series: To the right honorable and his singular good Lord Sir Henry Sidney knight of the most honorable Order of the Garter, Lord President of Wales, and matches of the same.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: News from the north.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴; A-L⁴ (missing A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Malta --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Nevves from Malta, written by a Gentleman of that Iland, to a friend of his in <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewing the desperate aſſault and ſurpriſing of tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Caſtles of the Turkes, by the Italians Forces, vpon the eight day of September laſt paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated according to the Italian Copie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Thomas Creede's device</figDesc>
               <p>TC</p>
               <q>VIRESS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>T VV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>NERE VERITAS</q>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Thomas Creede, for Iohn Hippon, and are to be ſold at his Shop in Watling-ſtreete, adioyning to the Red Lyon Gate. Anno. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:2"/>
            <head>To my very louing and much beloued Couzen, <hi>Signior M. P.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY good Couzen, I know you expect from me ſomewhat touching the occurrents of this place, the haſte of this bearer makes me brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer then I would be, yet as time would giue me leaue, I haue written you the truth of a peece of ſeruice lately done by our Cauelires and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, vppon two Caſtles of the Turkes, by the helpe of a Greeke: the maner whereof, and the meane whereby, I haue truly, though briefely ſet you down: in which I know you wil reioyce with vs in Chriſt, vnder whoſe banner we fight, and to whome wee giue the glory of our victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Malta</hi> 
                  <date>the 9. of October. 1603.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your very louing Couzen, P. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173301:2"/>
            <head>News from Malta, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a Gentleman of that Iland, to a friend of his in <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the moneth of September. 1603. about the eight day, the great maſter of our Iland, ſéeing the neceſſitie of Corne in this place, and determining by all meanes he could to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for the ſupply of ſuch want, had intelligence of a Grecian (who for ſome priuate diſcontentment in his boſome concealed, hauing ſtollen from the Turkes came vnto our Iland) that there was in two Caſtles of the ſaide Turkes great ſtore of Corne, lately laide in; and very ſhortly were two veſſels more of great burthen loaden with corne expected to come to them: all which if it would pleaſe our Gouernour to followe his aduiſe, he would not doubt to deliuer into his hands; who noting all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances by him deliuered, and vpon the nature of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment, the rather giuing credit to his report, did forthwith man out foure gallies with foure hundreth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Armes, and two Galleons with two hundreth ſouldiours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>diies, were a hundreth Knights of greate valor, and reſolution: who hauing put to ſea, with a proſperous winde, fell within a few dayes vpon the mouth of the Gulf, which brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder one of the Caſtles of the Turkes called <hi>Panto,</hi> about the twelfth hower of the night, where the Greeke with a better in his hand counterfaited for the purpoſe, being a ſhore with fifty of the Knights, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173301:3"/> and fifty ſouldiours, was deſcried by a <hi>Scintinell,</hi> ſtanding vpon the walls of the Caſtle: who cried out, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linga, chi va la?</hi> who goes there? was anſwered by the Gréeke, here is one come from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Baſſa to your Gouernor, who hath ſent me vnto him with this letter, and certaine ſouldiours to doe a ſodeine exploit of importance, ſo with a long ſpeare gaue him the letter: the watche, not miſtruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of any enemy, hauing drunke heard, and ſo fallen a ſléepe, the <hi>Scintinell</hi> carries the letter vnto the Gouernour, willing him to ſtaie, and he ſhould preſently haue his anſwer: which <hi>Scintinell,</hi> was no ſooner gone off the walls, but they hauing ſet vp their engines and lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſcaled the walls, entred the Caſtle, and hauing taken the ordinance, bent them againſt the houſe of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who vpon the ſhot of one Cannon, finding himſelfe betraied, came forth and ſubmitted himſelfe with all his people into the hands of our Caualierio, ſome fewe of the ſouldiours leaping ouer the walls, fledde away, in which time the other fifty Knights with a hundreth and fifty ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours going on ſhore vnder the other Caſtle, called <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractio,</hi> cauſing the Galleons to diſcharge a Bullet or two vpon the walles, the ſouldiers ſéeing the fifty of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the other caſtle, and hearing them crie, Treaſon treaſon, as men amazed, &amp; ſtrooken with a ſodain feare, left the caſtle, and made all the ſpéed they could to be gone to a cittie diſtance two miles or more from that place: ſo that our men entred the caſtle without reſiſtance: in which they found greate ſtore of corne, and other riches of good value: in the other Caſtle likewiſe they tooke beſides. Corne and other riches, the Gouernour, his Lady, and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, women of great beawty: all which, they with foure hundreth other ſouldiours, and other people, they brought home and ſolde for ſlaues to their great commodity: they tooke further, a hundreth great pieces of Artillery, of which were forty of Braſſe, full Cannons, and fit for battry: in theſe Caſtles they ſtaied foure dayes, expecting the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173301:3"/> of the greate ſhippes with corne, in which time the Turks fallying out of the Citie, made a brauado vpon our people, who encountring with them, ſlue ſome fifty of their van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and ſo draue them to retire: the next day following they made away our two Galleons brought with corne and ſpoile, beſide the foure hundreth ſlaues, which they ſent home, before them, the galleies ſtaying ſome halfe a day or more after them, putting out to Sea, met with the two ſhips loaden with corne, whom they tooke, with forty pieces of Ordinances, ten of them of braſſe, and foure Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, in the ſhippes they had a hundreth ſlaues, other wealth more then corne was little in them, but the veſſels were good and of good burthen: all which, with the loſſe but of one Caualierio, and ten ſouldiours, our men with great Triumphe brought home vnto our ports, to the greate glory of God, and the comfort of all Chriſtians. Had not the haſt of this bearer hindred me, I would more at large haue written vnto you of other points, as of the nature of the Gréekes diſcontentment, his reward from our Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for his ſeruice, who hath here a yearely penſion, and hath here ſet downe the ende of his daies amonge vs: God increaſe vs in theſe and other of his bleſſings, and ſend vs more ſuch good intelligence, for our comforts, and proſper vs in all ſuch and other enterpriſes, to his glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Right <hi>hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and his ſinguler good Lord Sir Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Sidney Knight of the moſte honorable <hi>Order of the</hi> Garter, <hi>Lord Preſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent</hi> of Wales, and Marches of the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough there can be no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reendſhip (right Honorable and my ſinguler good Lord) to ſpeak properly whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e there is no equallitie between the pa ties, yet may the ſimpleſt and the meaneſt looue and honor the higheſt and gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ateſt, yea ſo much the more as their inequallitie is the greater. But that is not properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led freendſhip but rather a dutifull looue and is harde to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and ſhewed for the inequalitie aforeſaid. For F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eendſhip is between equalls, or at the leaſt where the inequalliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not ſo very great that the Offices and duties of Freendſhip which are the bondes and ſinewes therof can haue no entercourſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I ſpeak this for my ſelf that haue long deſired occaſion to ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie goodwil and affection vnto your Lordſhip which hath been ſomewhat hard for me to doo for the cauſe abooue remembred. And therfore hauing gathered this little conference: I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade bold to dedicate it vnto my good Lord. A thing meeter to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my gift then woorthy to be preſented vnto your Honor or to go further vnder the name of ſuch a Patron. Howbeit, my truſt is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat your Lordſhip of your accuſtomed clemency will accept a ſimple thing of him at whoſe hands nothing at al was looked for, and will alowe my good will towards the reparation of ſuch faults and Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections as are heerin.</p>
            <p>So praying God to bleſſe your Lordſhip and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From London <date>the twentie ſix of Nouember. 1579.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all humillitie. T. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:5"/>
            <head>¶ TO THE GODLY and Gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast heer Godly and gentle <hi>Reader</hi>
               </hi> the Conference betwéen <hi>Sim Certain</hi> and <hi>Pierce Plowman</hi> two great Clarkes as thou maiſt vnderſtand by their Diſcourſe, which I haue gathered and reported as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and as truely as my ſimple memory could retaine the ſame, and that with ſome trauaile which I occounted my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Firſt vnto them and others by them héerin mentioned.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly vnto all and euery good man and woman whoſe mindes and harts God may ſturre vp vnto Godlynes and Vertue by their good enſample. Namely all ſuch as are Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Maiſters of houſholdes, but chéefly and principally of common Innes and Tauerns whoſe good or euill example ſpreadeth far and wide and I feare in theſe our daies rather in corruption of life and maners: then in edifiyng or increaſe of Vertue and Godlynes according to the ſaying of <hi>Ieſus</hi> of <hi>Sirach</hi> that it is as hard for a Merchant to be no lyar and for a Tauerner or Inholder to be no drunkerd which thing although hée hath ſaid to be very hard: yet (for the Inholder) that his rule admitteth exception, thou maiſt héer finde with out traueling to <hi>Rippon</hi> in Yorkſhire to learne and ſo for a grote or ſixpence thou maiſt know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which coſt mée aboue fiue markes to learne beſides my trauail and time ſpent, which yet if it pleaſe thée to accept: I ſhal account right wel beſtowed, which God graunt, and that in all thy Iourneis thy head ake not before thou alight in ſuch an Hoſtry. Farwel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aut bibe aut abi.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:5"/>
            <head>The Printer to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER, IF THOV</hi> finde any Imperfection in this woork either for the matter in ſubſtance or els for the deuiſion, the maner and forme therof I truſt thou wilt alow a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excuſe aſwel vnto the <hi>Author</hi> as vnto m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twen whome thy blame is otherwiſe to be deuided. Thou knoweſt that to write and reporte a thing at the mouth of the Speaker aſketh a nimble ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and a great memory, if a man had his Tooles ready for the purpoſe which yet this <hi>Author</hi> had not ready for nothing ſo like as any ſuch matter, and therfore was forced to put his braine-pan in truſt withall, and to write it in his way homeward.</p>
            <p>In dooing wherof his care was greater to couch the matter truely in ſubſtance: then to parte or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide or otherwiſe to digeſt the ſame. Which he refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto mee, and which alſo I haue doon as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the time gaue me leaue. Both which excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, if it pleaſe thee to admit: thou maiſt in time to come receiue it in more perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſwel for his part beeing the matter in ſubſtance wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I dout not much hath eſcaped him. and alſo for the diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beeing mine. Farwell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:6"/>
            <head>W. M. in Commendation <hi>of the Author.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eauing at large the Brunts of briniſh flood,</l>
               <l>The pitched Feelds and fables finely pend:</l>
               <l>This Author heer to doo his Cuntry good,</l>
               <l>One woork of woorth his time &amp; toile dooth ſpend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The buſie Brain with cankred Enuie fraught,</l>
               <l>That ſues and ſtriues for ſturring of a ſtraw:</l>
               <l>May read heerin his leſſon largely taught,</l>
               <l>And by the ſame deſcrie him ſelfe a Daw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Counſailer, the ſpokeſman, and the reſt,</l>
               <l>Who ſimple ſoules to needleſſe lawing eg:</l>
               <l>May learne heerby ſuch dealings to defame:</l>
               <l>As driue poor men their bread with teares to beg.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The prating Sot whoſe peremptory ſpeech,</l>
               <l>Is brayed foorth all Lawyers to defame:</l>
               <l>Not far from hence may finde a cunning Leech,</l>
               <l>To charme his tung and ſhroud it in with ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But in few woords my meaning to imparte,</l>
               <l>If you demaund what mine opinion is:</l>
               <l>Hee hath doon wel, Gods bleſſing on his hart,</l>
               <l>Who ſend me ſtore of Books ſo good as this.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Coelum non Solum. W. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anthony Munday to all curteous</hi> and freendly Readers in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <hi>of this</hi> Woork.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Tully did of vertuous life define,</l>
               <l>And Ouid paint the odde conceits of looue:</l>
               <l>And Maro ſquared in a direct line,</l>
               <l>The hard aſſaults that valiant harts did proue,</l>
               <l>In bloody Battails for their fames behoue.</l>
               <l>As fliering Fortune ſhould them chaunce to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y:</l>
               <l>In vaunting verſe as Maro tells the way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But leauing now at large ſuch fond delights,</l>
               <l>Such Fables fond as pratling Poets vſe:</l>
               <l>This Author heer preſenteth to your ſights,</l>
               <l>Such tales of trueth as may you force to muſe,</l>
               <l>To iudge aright the crime of eche abuſe.</l>
               <l>As heer twixt Sim and Pierce he dooth comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und:</l>
               <l>Such wiſe conceits as ſeldome hath been fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When you haue read Iudge then the Authors pains.</l>
               <l>His tedious toyle in wiſhing well to thee:</l>
               <l>Thy freendly thanks, he craues no other gaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Which vnto him more welcome ſure ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>Then riches ſtore if thou couldſt giue it free.</l>
               <l>Wherfore my Freends doo this at my requeſt</l>
               <l>To heare and ſee and alway ſay the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Honos alit Artes. A. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:7"/>
            <head>* Thomas Procter in reporte of the Authors good wil.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the woorthy woorks,</l>
            <l>whith learned <hi>Tully</hi> pend:</l>
            <l>The care of Cuntrie and of Freends,</l>
            <l>he greatly dooth commend.</l>
            <l>¶ Which leſſon in my minde,</l>
            <l>the Man which took in hand:</l>
            <l>To pen this pleaſant Hiſtory,</l>
            <l>did perfect vnderſtand.</l>
            <l>¶ For in the ſame he ſhowes,</l>
            <l>a looue vnto his Frends:</l>
            <l>Beſide a zealous minde of good,</l>
            <l>that to his Cuntrie tends.</l>
            <l>¶ Of <hi>Louers</hi> liues, of <hi>Warres,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>ne yet of <hi>Wunders</hi> great:</l>
            <l>Hee ſeemes to publiſh vnto vs,</l>
            <l>but ſimply dooth intreat.</l>
            <l>¶ Of ſilly Men, whoſe proof,</l>
            <l>dooth ſuch experience giue:</l>
            <l>As for Examples of our liues,</l>
            <l>learnes eche eſtate to liue.</l>
            <l>¶ Wherin the <hi>Author</hi> ſought,</l>
            <l>ſuch meanes to publiſh it:</l>
            <l>As in my ſimple Iudgement ſure,</l>
            <l>might ſeem to prooue his wit.</l>
            <l>¶ But for the careful paines,</l>
            <l>which he hath ſpent heerin:</l>
            <l>Hee only craues for recompence,</l>
            <l>your fauours good to win.</l>
            <l>¶ wherby you may him mooue,</l>
            <l>to vtter his good wil:</l>
            <l>when as occaſion ſhall him ſerue,</l>
            <l>in woorks of greater ſkil.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Nil Melius Arte. T. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:7"/>
            <head>✿ Iohn Peeterhouſe to the Reporter of this Hiſtorie.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that haſt reported this pleaſant Hiſtory,</l>
            <l>Wherof thine eyes and eares are a witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe:</l>
            <l>And haſt intreaſured the memory,</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Pierce</hi> and <hi>Simon</hi> for their woorthines,</l>
            <l>Withouten hope of hire or recompe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce:</l>
            <l>For thy long Iourney, or for thy diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence.</l>
            <l>¶ Thou haſt acquit thy dutie vnto them,</l>
            <l>In this behalf, and if I geſſe aright:</l>
            <l>Thou haſt deſerued well of other men,</l>
            <l>Before whome thou haſt ſet a Candle light.</l>
            <l>Of Nurture and of Education:</l>
            <l>By men of baſe and mean condition.</l>
            <l>¶ Which ſome for that cauſe wil eſtéem the leſſe,</l>
            <l>Hauing reſpect vnto the circumſtaunce:</l>
            <l>The great apparaunce of vnliklyneſſe,</l>
            <l>Waying all others in their owne ballaunce.</l>
            <l>As if that God could not reſerue a few:</l>
            <l>Such as him liſt his glory for to ſhew.</l>
            <l>¶ For what though this age vniuerſally,</l>
            <l>Séemeth geuen ouer to corruption:</l>
            <l>Séemed it not ſo in the dayes of <hi>Elie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When yet God had reſerued many a one?</l>
            <l>So hath he now, that are not gon aſide:</l>
            <l>Nor ſolde them ſelues to Couetiſe and Pride.</l>
            <l>¶ As thou haſte well ſhewed in this Hiſtory,</l>
            <l>What by thine owne proofe and experience:</l>
            <l>What by thine Hoſte <hi>Simons</hi> authoritie,</l>
            <l>Which (for mine owne parte) I doo reuerence,</l>
            <l>And therfore (I ſay thank come to thy hand,</l>
            <l>That haſte it geuen vs to vnderſtand.</l>
            <l>¶ And putteſt vs in hope that Charitie,</l>
            <l>Is not ſtark dead though ſhe be wounded ſore:</l>
            <l>By Pride and Couetiſe her enemy,</l>
            <l>And that our God yet kéepeth ſome in ſtore.</l>
            <l>That both in déed and woord doo ſéek his praiſe</l>
            <l>God let them wax and giue them happy daies.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:8"/>
            <head>¶ The Reporter to his Book.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>My little Book where ſo thou chaunce to dwel,</l>
               <l>God giue thee fauour in thy Readers ſight:</l>
               <l>Whom if thou pleaſe all, thou muſt quit thee well,</l>
               <l>And better then I feare is in thy might.</l>
               <l>For that dooth ſeldome chaunce to any one:</l>
               <l>Better or wurſſe without exception.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ If any man or woman chalenge thee,</l>
               <l>For any woord or any argument:</l>
               <l>Come not to ſeek thy defence at mee,</l>
               <l>For I am not thine Author Verament.</l>
               <l>Get thee into the North to <hi>Rippon</hi> Town:</l>
               <l>And there enquire for <hi>Pierce</hi> that woorthy clown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And eke for <hi>Simon Certain</hi> at the Signe</l>
               <l>Of the Greek <hi>Omega</hi> there dooth hee dwell:</l>
               <l>where welcome thou ſhalt be as I diuine,</l>
               <l>Aſke them whether thou haſt reported well.</l>
               <l>Their conference according to the trueth:</l>
               <l>If they ſay yea, of others haue no rueth.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:8"/>
            <head>How the Author comming homeward out of Scotland through Yorkſhire, chaunced to lodge in Rippon, At what ſigne, the name of the Hoſte, the order and maner of the Houſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melye. And his entertaiment there. Chap. 1.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my laſt return from Edenborough in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> comming homeward through <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire:</hi> I traueled ſomewhat out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon high London way, of purpoſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſée the Cuntrie. And one day among oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward euen: I chaunced to come to a little through fare Towne called <hi>Rippon,</hi> where at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the town I met a poore olde Woman, of whom I aſked if there were any good lodging in the town. She anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red mee that there was good lodging at the ſigne of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Gréek <hi>Omega.</hi> The Gréek <hi>Omega</hi> (quoth I) What doo yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> meane by that? Nothing ſaid ſhe, but that there is good lodging and honeſt entertainment, which (I ſuppoſe) is all tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Then I aſked her what was the good mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame of the houſe. His name (quoth ſhe) is <hi>Simon Certain</hi> we call him commonly <hi>Sim Certain. Sim Certain</hi> (quoth I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſurely theſe are very ſtrange names, and ſo bidding her fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewell: I departed into the towne warde, much more deſire is to be come to my lodging, for the ſtrangenes of the names, aſwell of the Signe: as alſo of the Good man of the Houſe. By that time I had entred a little way into the Town: I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ware of a very faire Gréek <hi>Omega</hi> hanging foorth as a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmon Signe, euen as the olde woman had tolde me before. And thether I went, and entring into the houſe: I foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Hall the Good man, his two Sonnes, his Chamberl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in, and his Hoſtler ſinging the Ciiij. Pſalme of <hi>Dauid</hi> very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and orderly. The Goodwife with her two Daugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers ſat ſpinning at their Whéeles a little diſtaunce from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m. All which things when I beheld: I thought with my ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe that theſe things were yet more ſtrange to beholde, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were
<pb facs="tcp:173301:9"/> either the Signe or els the good mans name to heare. So I bad them God ſpéed. The Hoſte very curteouſly aroſe, and bad me welcome, ſo did the wife alſo, and aſked mée whether I meant to tary all night. I anſwered yea. Then he aſked mée if I would ſée my Chamber. No gentle Hoſte (quoth I) I will not hinder ſo much your good exerciſe, for I am ſure I cannot be lodged amiſſe in this houſe. Not ſo ſir (quoth he) but ye ſhall haue the beſt that we haue and welcome. I gaue him harty thanks. Then hée enquired of mée, of whence I was, where I had béen, and whether I was bound. I tolde him I was a Southern man borne and dwelling, and that I had béen at <hi>Edenborough</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and was thus farre in my way homeward. In good time ſir (quoth hée) and yée are hartely welcome into this part of Yorkſhire. I thank you gentle Hoſte (quoth I.)</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>The comming thether of Pierce Plowman, beeing newly come from London. His requeſt to the Hoſte to lend him fiue pound vpon a paune. The refuſall of the Hoſte, the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereupon moued, beeing the matter of the conference. Chap. 2.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y that time we had talked ſcant half an hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: there came in a Cuntrie man a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, a iolly olde fatherly man, bringing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his arme a fardell of Bookes, as many as hée might well holde vnderneath one of his armes, he gaue vs the time of the day. What Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte) welcome from London Sir (quoth he to me) this Neighboure of mine is lately come from where you are going God willing. Truely (qooth I) and this is happily met by grace of God, and as I verily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe néere in the mid way betwéene <hi>Edenborough</hi> and Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. With that Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth this <hi>Pierce</hi> Plow man (for that was his name) I am come to deſire your help. What is the matter Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte?)
<pb facs="tcp:173301:9"/> Neighbour (quoth hée) to lend mée fiue pound for half a yéer, for truely (quoth hée) I haue ſpent all my mony at London, and haue not left my ſelf ſo much as to buy my ſéed Wheat, wherwith to ſowe my land this ſeaſon. No haue neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth hée) that was very ill handled, ye ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſo vſe your matters that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> main ſtock be ſau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d whole. Fye neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth he, ſpeak no more of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for the reuerence of God, for truely I am aſhamed of my ſelf, but what remedy now ſaue patience, and to learne to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e wiſer héeafter. What meanes all theſe paper Books (quoth our Hoſte. Mary neighbour quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> they ſhalbe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>retie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you for the repaiment of your fiue pound. With that they were vnbound, and béeing opened and looked vpon: t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey were Billes, Anſwers, Replications, Reionders Coppie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Depo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitions, and ſuch like. Some out of one Court, ſome out of an other. When our Hoſte had ſéen them all: why Neighbour (quoth hée) doo you think to méet with any man that is ſo mad to lend v. pence vpon ſuch traſh? Traſh Neighbour quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> they ſtand me in aboue fiftie pound. Peradventure ſo quoth our Hoſte, but that prooueth not that they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e woorth fiftie points, ſauing vnto him that were as mad to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uy them of you: as you bought them at their hands that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lde them vnto you. But or you méet with any ſuch chapman: I beléeue you will be weary of kéeping them. With that <hi>Pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi> began to be half offended. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoſte, fiue pound is a ſmall matter betwéen vs twain, you ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all haue it vpon your woord. But as for your Books: héer d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elleth a Lady not far hence, carie them to her, for they are f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r fet and déer bought, and ſuch things men ſay are good for Ladies.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Pierce findeth it ſtrange that men ſhould pay ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eer for things which in their hands are ſo vile and little woorth, as concerning their return. Chap. 3.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:10"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) I can put vp that mock at your hands, for I knowe ye meane me no euil but good therby, but veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly me thinketh it ſtandeth hardly with their exiſtimation that will be holden and termed woorſhipfull yea honorable, to take ſo extrem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for things, wherof no better returne is to be made, yet muſt wée pay them with great attendaunce, with cap in hand and all reuerence. Great reaſon quoth our Hoſte, for they are woorſhipfull, and right woorthy of all thoſe duties. Then haue I béen in an errour a long time (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) for I haue alwaies hetherto thought that woorſhip and honor had ſtood in geuing: &amp; not in taking, in helping, reléeuing and doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good: and not in their contraries, and this ſéemeth vnto mée both reaſonable and alſo common experience, for we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God at whoſe hands we receiue all goodnes, and therfore properly vnto him is all honor and woorſhip due, and vnto men but ſo far foorth as they approchen vnto God in qualitie of vertue, iuſtice, mercy and other goodnes, wherfore in all reaſon he ought to be moſte honorable and woorſhipfull that dooth the moſte good, and vnto the greateſt number, for ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in my diſcretion, the woorſhip and the gaine ought to bée deuided, and he that gayneth, or is reléeued, and is holpen: ought to honor and woorſhip him by whom he gayneth, is hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen and reléeued, for otherwiſe why dooth the Seruant woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip his Maiſter and not <hi>e conuerſo.</hi> Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoſte, our honorable &amp; reuerend forefathers with great wiſdome and diſcretion, aſſeſſed theſe Fées and charges, and that for the great zeale and looue which they bare vnto God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and vertue, and to the perſons quallified therwith.</p>
            <p>With <hi>P</hi> that <hi>ierce</hi> clapped his hand vpon the boord. I make God a vow (quoth hée) whatſoeuer he was that firſt praiſed a ſhéet of paper with twelue lines written therin at eight pence, nay at xij. pence, for I am ſure I haue CC. that coſt me after that rate, he was neither fréend to godlynes ne vertue, to God, neither to good man or woman. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoſte, this is but the errour of your Iudgement,
<pb facs="tcp:173301:10"/> and that ſhall appéere vnto you ſo euidently, that your ſelf ſhall confeſſe that theſe fées and charges which you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hink ſo great and ſo excceſſiue had ſo great reaſon in their beginning as that greater had neuer any ciuil ordinance or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itution. Whether yée will regarde the honor and glory of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d or the preſeruation of the common Welth which chéefly de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endeth therupon. That ſéemeth wunderfull ſtrange vnto m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) that in ſuch extreme taking and ſo ſmall rendring there ſhould lye hidden ſo great miſtery of good meaning and therfore gladly would I heare your reaſons therupon. Very well Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth hée) then I will take in hand to prooue it vnto you, which I truſt I ſhall doo ſufficiently if I can prooue theſe are no proper nor priuate gain or proffit, but a publique and a common treaſure to the eaſe and reléef of the whole common welth and of the beſt and godli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt &amp; Mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers of the ſame, yea verily (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) very well (quoth our Hoſte.)</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Simon approoueth their great Fees and charges as things ment to be a reward and nuriſhment of Knowledge, lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing and Vertue, and puniſhment of vngodlines and vice, and therfore true and iuſt. Chap. 4.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt I think yée will graunt (quoth h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e) that Maieſtrates and Officers are the Deputies and Liuetenaunts of GOD héerin Earth, high and honorable, for that they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n very déed the hand and mouth of the Lawe, and in fewe and plain woords the ſpeaking a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Law, for by them the law commandeth and forbiddeth So that their end and purpoſe is that God may be honored and glorified, good and godly People cheriſhed, ſhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly that peace and concord may be maintained. I graunt you all this (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) you will graunt (quoth hée) that ſhe way and meane to woork all theſe things is to puniſh and chaſtice the wicked and the vngodly, and to giue as little fauour vnto ſinne as is poſſible, that is very true alſo (quoth <hi>Pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi>) Yée will graunt (quoth our Hoſte) that the wayes and meanes to
<pb facs="tcp:173301:11"/> puniſh ſinnes and wickednes are diuers, according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie of the offence, as ſome by death, ſome by other punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the body greater or ſmaller. And that there is alſo a pecuniall puniſhment by the purſſe, as by fine and ranſome, and ſuch like. I graunt you all this (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>). You will graunt me alſo (quoth hée) that all puniſhments are gréeuous vnto the ſufferers therof, neither are or ought to be pleaſant vnto the dooers and executors. That is very true alſo quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> except they be wicked perſons both the ſufferer and the executor. Then quoth our Hoſte, ſéeing all puniſhments are fearfull and gréeuous vnto the ſufferer therof, &amp; no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but rather ſorrowe and gréef of hart vnto the executors therof, ſuch and ſo muſt néeds be the firſt cauſes and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therof. That is very true quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> You know quoth our Hoſte, that the cauſes and occaſions of puniſhment is ſin, wickednes and miſgouernment of life, for the woord of God telleth vs, that the reward of ſinne is death. All that is very true quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> Very well then quoth our Hoſte, theſe Propoſitions which you haue graunted: doo ſuffiſe for the matter which I haue taken in hand to prooue, which is, that theſe great Fées and charges were neuer ment, nor yet are receiued or conuerted into priuat or proper vſe. I pray you Neighbour quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> let me heare how it is prooued, for I promiſe you faithfully for any thing I haue yet heard: your prooues are farther to fet.</p>
            <p>You know quoth our Hoſte, that the nature of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly is to be quarelous and contencious, and dayly prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one an other, and alſo to take no wrong and do no right. That is very true quoth <hi>pierce.</hi> You know quoth our Hoſte that the common weapon wherwith they wil be aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vpon eche other is the Law, which indéed is the Magiſtrate, as ye haue already graunted, ſo that vpon the matter: hée is made the executor of their wilfunes and vengeaunce, which they will néeds doo vpon eche other, which thing you haue already confeſſed to be gréeuous and vnpleaſant to euery good man. Therfore hath it euer béen, and yet is thought, and that very wiſely and truely, that the likelieſt way &amp; meane to diſſwade
<pb facs="tcp:173301:11"/> their wilfulnes which no reaſon, looue nor feare of GOD could diſſwade was to make their wilfulnes as déere and as heauy vnto them as reaſonably might be doon, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that they ſhould not ſo lightly and for euery trifle vex and trouble both the Magiſtrate &amp; one an other, which effect although it failed to woork, &amp; that their madnes would not be reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rayned therby: that yet their vngodlynes might return to the profit and reléefe of others their neighbours &amp; Brethern that were better affected, &amp; ſo by one ſelfe and ſame mean: the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngodly puniſhed &amp; fléeced, and the godly amended &amp; inriched herby, &amp; that this was their meaning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was the firſt aſſeſſors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: common experience teacheth vs, for in néedfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary actions, as debt, detinew, and account and ſuch like: the charges are ſo reaſonable, as that no man would in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience giue leſſe.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is, for that they are actions of common right, and ſuch as muſt néeds day by day ariſe betwéen a man and his Brother, neither doo they diſhoneſt either of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arties which I dare not affirme vpon actions vpon caſes, neither did they ſo iudge of them, as I verily beléeue, and therfore did they ſet double and treble charges thereupon, for greater is the charges in a brabble for a woord ſpoken: then f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r thrée hundred pound of honeſt debt.</p>
            <p>So that the Magiſtrate, who for ſuch Ale-houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions and brabbles: ſhould otherwiſe neuer be at reſt, except he ſhould deny them his help, which might be ſlaunder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us and perillous to the whole eſtate.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrate I ſay of pure pittie and compaſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, was forced to ſet great charges vpon them, for the ſmall fauour that he bare vnto them, &amp; vnto their firſt cauſes &amp; occaſions.</p>
            <p>The greatnes of all which charges not withſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, yet doo we dayly ſée how the vngodly run togither by hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s like brute beaſts, and yet I dare ſafely ſay, that by the greatnes of theſe charges, and the terrour therof: many a brabling matter hath béen and is dayly put vp without any r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uenge ſought therof, and many a one hauing purſued and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his action, yet haue his charges ſo gallded him: that
<pb facs="tcp:173301:12"/> he hath béen eaſier to deale with all his life after. And ſo by this meane many a wilfull body brought to knowe him ſelf: and to honor God therby.</p>
            <p>I cannot tell Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> but I my ſelf haue had two or thrée brabbles that haue kept me dooing theſe ſeuen yéeres, in which time I am ſuer I haue ſpent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booue fiftie pound, beſide my charges to and fro, loſſe of time, and my hinderance at home. And what haue ye gotten for all this quoth our Hoſte? Theſe papers quoth he. Wel woorth fiftie points quoth our hoſte. I think verily quoth our Hoſte if any honeſt Neighbour had néeded to haue borowed ten pound therof: you would not haue it ſo ready to haue pleaſured him withall. If I ſhould ſay truely (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) I think the very ſame. What are you aſſeſſed vnto the poore in your Pariſh quoth our Hoſte? A peny a wéek quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> And think you that enough quoth our Hoſte? Yea verily quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> Loe Sir quoth our Hoſte, whether commeth this vnto my ſaying and maintenaunce of theſe great Fées and charges or not? Who can deny the excellency of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution? wherby the Couetuous and vngodly men are ſhot one againſt an other, and doo puniſh eche other, and wherby alſo ſo plentiful prouiſion is made for the godly poore at their charges, and yet no thank to them therfore, and that thoſe things from the which they would depart vnto any Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or godly vſe or purpoſe, with as good will as from their eyes to be plucked out of their heads, or their tripes out of their bellyes, by this meane vndeſired of their owne accord, they bring it in by handfuls, and ſo as it hath béen ſaid, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful prouiſion made for their godly Neighbours at their charges and yet no thank vnto them therfore.</p>
            <p>Call you this a prouiding for the poore? Neighbour (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) I would I had giuen you the beſt horſe in my Plough to make this ſaying true, and I ſweare to you (quoth he) prooue it true: and you ſhall haue him yet or this day Seuen night, for that would eaſe my hart if I might perceiue that any godly perſon hath fared the better or were amended by any parte of all my great expences. For then yet ſhould I
<pb facs="tcp:173301:12"/> think that I haue doone ſome good with all the loſſe of my mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney. Why Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth <hi>Simon</hi>) doo you doubt that all theſe ſummes or the greateſt part therof: commeth not to the vſe of the common wealth, and to the reliefe and ſuſtenance of the godly poore, and other eaſements of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things in maintenaunce of the common Wealt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? Nay Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth he) I doubt it not, for I am fully perſwaded the contrary. Truely Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth he) this is an vncharitable and a very erronious op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inion, and that I will proue vnto you by reaſons manifeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, and ſuch as your ſelf haue alredy graunted &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfeſſed. I pray you neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> let me hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e how.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Simon approoueth theſe fees and charges as publi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue and not priuat, by argument taken from effects vnto thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſes. Chap. 5.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoeuer he be that Coueteth priuately to gaine and profit by any thing (quoth our Hoſte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) coueteth the thing wherby he gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and profiteth, this is ſo true (quoth he) that I will not deſire you to graunt t vnto me, for it is a neceſſary argument from the effect vnto the cauſe, and therfore if ye wil affirm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the Magiſtrate and officer coueteth theſe great fées and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>harges and priuately to thriue and wax rich therby: you muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily conclude, that he fauoureth all the firſt &amp; mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſes therof, which were a horrible &amp; a fearfull concluſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet as I haue ſaid followeth neceſſarily vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> premiſes g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aunted &amp; therfore is couetiſe ſo much more odious &amp; deteſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le in a Magiſtrate then in a common perſon, for couetiſe as he excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all other vices ſimply conſidered: euen ſo reſpecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely he excéedeth him ſelf, I ſay reſpectiuely to wit, qualifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the perſon in whome he dwelleth, for in a priuat perſon: he is but a priuat ſin, &amp; extendeth vnto his M. only, but in a Magiſtrate he is a publique and general corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, for ther's no couetoꝰ perſon béeing but a priuate man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any other to be ſuch as they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues are, the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon is, for that the Couetiſe of others: is nothing whereby they
<pb facs="tcp:173301:13"/> ſhould gayne or be aduaunced, but rather loſe therby.</p>
            <p>Therfore could they be content that there were few or no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſuch as they are, wherby it apéereth that couetiſe in a priuate Perſon neither woorketh nor wiſheth any general corruption and yet fulfilleth the talent and habit of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and ſo much the more. The very ſame is to be ſaid of all other vices in all other perſons without exception of degrée, as Whoordome, Pride, Gluttony, Drunkennes and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exceſſe in voluptuous pleaſure, in al which things what ſoeuer hath or euer had the greateſt felicitie &amp; enioyed moſte therof: yet would they not that others did the like, or at the leaſt no more then they them ſelues muſte neceſſarily vſe for the accompliſhment of their pleaſures which requireth ſome company. The reaſon is already ſhewed, to wit for the other Folkes pleaſures are not their pleaſures, neither doo increaſe the ſame, but rather their paines and miſery.</p>
            <p>For the hunger, ſcarcitie and want of others giueth a good taſte and ſauour vnto the voluptuouſnes and pleaſures of the vngodly, and therfore could they be very wel content to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy their owne wickednes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, for pleaſure haue they none nor gain in the lewdnes or the miſgouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of other. And if they had: yet want they power to corrupt others ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by otherwiſe then by example which can not doo much in any one priuate man or woman, for that they haue but the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their owne liues. But of Couetiſe in the Magiſtrate it is otherwiſe, for hée hath the leading and the fourming of other mens liues and therfore differeth from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon and priuate perſon both concerning his wil and alſo concerning his habilitie and power to execute the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶ Firſt concerning deſire and will: hée cannot wiſh that the common people ſhould be godly and vertuous, for neither ſtandeth his great gain, nor his Ambition therin, for why they are two things incompacible and contrary.</p>
            <p>Then concerning his power to execute his wil and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: it is ſo great and ſo mighty that the olde Proouers hath no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubted to call the common People the Image of their Magiſtrates and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ficers for as certainly as this antecedent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:13"/>
            <p>The man eateth and drinketh inferreth this co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſequent the man is a liue: euen ſo certainly this propoſitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and officers are couetous inferreth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion.</p>
            <p>The People are vngratious and vngodly. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſon is peremptory for the Magiſtrate and Officer hath t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Bridle rain in his hand either to giue libertie vnto vngodl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes and diſſolution of life: or els to refrain the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now all men may dayly ſée by proof that there is no wilde Beaſt ſo very brute and barbarous as man will war and hée through libertie and that for the excellency of h s nature abooue all other Creatures and his great vnderſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nding in good and euil.</p>
            <p>¶ And therfore to admit in a Magiſtrate a coue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe and a deſire of priuate and proper gain, Namely by fées <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ariſing and growing is as alredy confeſſed, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe were to conclude an odious and deteſtable Conſequence againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrate and Officer of whome wée are forbidde: by God to ſpeak or think ſaue all honor and reuerence.</p>
            <p>¶ Wherfore I ſay it ſtandeth not with the reue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence and honourable opinion that wée are bound to haue of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to ſay or to think that theſe great gaines &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to him in priuate and proper vſe: but rather t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iudge &amp; think that the Magiſtrate &amp; Officer receiueth them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s things excommunicate and as a common Treaſure dedic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted vnto godly vſes and purpoſes in eaſe and reléef of the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</p>
            <p>¶ Would God this were true quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> for I da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lay my life (quoth hée) that if all the ſummes of money that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re leud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſhamefully ſpent in one Terme about vain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tes and brabbles were reſerued and accounted in the end of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Term: they would amount to more then all the Collectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the Poore through out all the pariſhes in England for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf a yéer neuertheleſſe many a o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thinketh him ſelfe ſore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>harged, namely my ſelfe God forgiue mée.</p>
            <p>Truely Neighbour (quoth our Hoaſt) I am of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o other Opinion, neither doo I Iudge that all theſe great Fées and Reuenewes are any other thing but a Collection fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſes
<pb facs="tcp:173301:14"/> and intents aforeſaid, neither that the receiuers of the ſame doo differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe other Collectors in pariſh Churches ſauing in the greatnes of their receit and alſo ſauing that they are not forced to craue it at the parties hands and ſome time to conuent him before a Iuſticer of peace for a grote or ſix pence as the others oft times are. And alſo ſauing that for their reuerend and honorable eſtemation they are not accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Sauing vnto the Lord God the Author generall and vnto their owne Conſciences.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Pierce denyeth the reaſons alleaged as probable but not neceſſary. His reaſons therfore. Chap. 6.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> you haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged many fair and coulorable propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and concluſions and haue gone about mée w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this reaſon and with that.</p>
            <p>I am no Schoole man, Neighbour quoth hée, but yet ſome reaſon I haue and ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience I haue ſéen, and ſome héed I haue taken thereof, wherfore if you wil giue mée leaue to anſwere you: you ſhall hear mée as probably diſprooue theſe your allegations as you prooued them, for I ſhall proue all your propoſitions are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable and not neceſſary, neither doo inferre a neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion as you haue pretended. For the better dooing wherof: firſt for orders ſake, I wil rehearſe your propoſitions, reaſons and arguments, wherof the firſt is, that the Magiſtrate and Officer is to be had in all honor and reuerence becauſe hée is the Law which is moſte honorable and reuerend, this I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe as an vndoubted trueth, namely for that the end aſwel of the one as of the other, is that God may be honored and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, godly People cheriſhed, and maintaine peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſtrengthned and furthered, wherupon ſtandeth the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie &amp; the good eſtate of all Cuntries and common welths, their wayes and meanes you haue alleaged are theſe.</p>
            <p>To puniſh and chaſtice the wicked and the vngodly, and to reſtraine their libertie as much as is poſſible. Yée haue fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther alleaged that puniſhments are diuers, ſome corporall,
<pb facs="tcp:173301:14"/> ſome pecuniall, and that all puniſhments are gréeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us bothe vnto the ſufferers, and alſo vnto the dooers therof, but that I wil not graunt ye without diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Very true it is that all puniſhments without e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ception, are gréeuous vnto the ſufferers therof, but vnto the executor therof: they are not all ſo, namely ſuch as are pecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iall and the gaine therof returning vnto the executor. For although that to beat, burn, hang or whip any creature of God, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Chriſtian man or woman: is an odious thing &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no good or Godly hart can haue pleaſure: yet for aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſake it is often otherwiſe, for otherwiſe ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would not ſo many Oxen, Shéep and Calues be murthere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo few Hogs, Dogges or Cats, their offences béeing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly their good fleſh.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, although that in all Godly reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments haue great neceſſitie: yet in humaine reaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience it hath but bare probabilitie and is no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re. But as if for example you wil ſay Women ought to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhamed to be ſéen bibbing wine in common Tauernes, or to be ſéen at common laſciuious and bawdie Stage Playes: therfore they are aſhamed therof.</p>
            <p>This is an argument gathered from <hi>poſſe</hi> to <hi>eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to wit, from ſhould or ought to be, to is ſimply, and hath not any neceſſitie nor firmitie, and that ſhall you ſee if you will goe with me to London this next Terme.</p>
            <p>How be it, you ſéem to inforce your anteceden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, by the honorable exiſtimation wherin I am bound to haue the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and Officer, and therby you think that of dutie I ought to graunt it you for the ſhamefull conſequenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whiche neceſſarily enſueth vpon the deniall therof.</p>
            <p>Truely that notwithſtanding, me thinketh all this but a very bare and naked proof.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:15"/>
            <head>¶ Simon maintaineth his aſſertion by authoritie of holy Scripture and diuerſitie taken between the reward of Vertue, Learning and Knowledge and the hire of ſeruile trauaile and labour. Cap. 7.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>All you this a bare and naked proof Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoaſt, if you denye this proof (quoth hée) you reuerſe &amp; ouerthrow all humain ſocietie which is maintained and vpholden by giuing vnto God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is due vnto God, and vnto man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is due vnto man. But vnto God what can wée giue ſaue honor, praiſe &amp; glory, firſt and immediatly vnto him ſelf, and ſecondly vnto his Deputies and Lieutenants, to wit, Magiſtrates &amp; Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers whoſe calling and appointing therunto as it is of God: ſo muſt and ought wée to think that it is for their godlynes and vertues, for God him ſelfe hath ſaid them that honor me I will honor, and they that diſhonour mée I wil diſhonour, wherfore our wiſe and reuerend Elders and Forefathers in their aſſeſſing theſe great fées and charges: did mean to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor them whome God honoured. And therfore vnto their cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lings appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted they great and honorable reuenues, knowing that their gain is the puniſhment of vice and the rewarde of Vertue, and that the part &amp; portion of all the godly is therin, knowing alſo that there is not ſo great Incouragement vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Vertue and Godlynes: as the liberall rewarde therof, and that all vngodlynes and vnthankfulnes is meaſured by the greatnes of thy goodnes and benefit receiued either at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of God or man. Laſtly knowing that they might not proſecute but perſecute the cauſes &amp; occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of theſe gains as hath alre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy béen prooued, and therfore I ſay abooue all common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and diſcretion they aſſeſſed theſe Fées and reuenues that the gains might be great and yet the cauſes therof few, quite contrarie to all other eſtates and faculties, for what other reaſon is there that one man ſhall labour ſore a whole day &amp; at night ſhall receiue twelue pence or eight pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for his hire: Another for half or a quarter of an houres eaſie trauail ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:173301:15"/> receiue xx. ſhillings or ſometime more, what is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſe of this diuerſitie? euen this, the one is a hire and a pric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile labour and trauell, and is receiued in proper a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d priuat vſe, the other is an honor doone vnto vertue, Godl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes and knowledge: which doo receiue nor holde, or accou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t any ſo baſe things proper or priuate, or can be ſo baſely m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded, as to ioy therin, further then they may glorify God the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>by.</p>
            <p>what other reaſon is there, that one man in the returne of a Reame of paper, ſhall gaine xij. pence or xvi. pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce cléer, and yet where he layd out ij. pence: the other laid ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> x. ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. And after the ſame rate in Wax, that one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an ſhall ſell more for vi. pence: then an other ſhall ſell for viij pound, which neuertheleſſe bought as déer as he, within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ij. pence at xx. ſhillings waring, and both laid out more mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, &amp; lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger looked for the return therof. I ſay there is no rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on other then is already made.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Pierce denyeth the calling to office, to be ſuch as Simon hath alleaged. Cap. 8.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ras you maintaine your aſſerſion by the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthines of the Magiſtrate and Officer, and doo inſiſt thervpon, alledging that they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alled by God, and that for their godlines an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vertue. The firſt part I greatly dout, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t many of them buy their offices, and pay very déerly therf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, yea ſome ſell their very inheritaunces for that purpoſe, I mean to buy offices, now did I neuer read that euer God receiued Money for an office, how be it I referre my ſelf héer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to my Maiſters that are learned.</p>
            <p>The next part that they are called for their V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtue and Godlines, ſurely then I verily ſuppoſe ſome of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the things that neuer were in them before, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd then were the caller deceiued, which God cannot be, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cept you will ſay that God of his méere goodnes and mercy called them
<pb facs="tcp:173301:16"/> for the vertues and godlynes which he meaneth to call them vnto, and in this order beginneth to woork, I meane in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo liberally, and by that meanes to charge them with his expectation, in reſpect of their great Tallent committed vnto them, which thing you ſéem to alledge, as no ſmall cauſe and conſideration of the high aſſeſſing of the fées and charges aforeſaid, and that ſo great mercies &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beſtowed vpon them by God, and ſo liberall reward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vnto them by men: ſhould ſuffiſe to make them god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vertuous from thence foorth: what ſo euer they were or had béen before. All which arguments, although they be godly and probable: yet as I ſaid before they ſtand doubtful, for the olde Prouerb, Honors chaunge manners. I beléeue the godly and the learned doo dout whether it be taken in the better part, or in the wurſſe, for I am very ſure, that many are wurſe diſpoſed, and much more vngodly in high and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable calling: then while they were in meane eſtate and degree.</p>
            <p>Neighboure <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte) there is no rule ſo generall, that it admitteth not exception, albeit I dout not nor euer did, that honours chaunge manners, is and euer was meant in the better parte. For the wiſeman ſaith. He that is vngodly in welth: how much more vngodly would he be in pouertie? The examples are many that doo prooue that honors chaunge men to the better, namely of <hi>Saule,</hi> of whome it is ſaid that béeing called from a ſimple boy after his Inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration: he felt him ſelfe ſuddainly chaunged, and as the book ſaith: he felt a new hart in him.</p>
            <p>The like example we haue of many Kings and Prophets in the Scripture. But to come néerer, both for the time and alſo the place, in our Engliſh Hiſtory we read of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble King H. the fifth, who in his Fathers life was of euil go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and kept company with riotors and vnthrifts, ſo that there was ſmall hope of him, but after the death of H. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth, when this yung man was placed in his kingdom: he ſent for all his olde companions, who were not a little glad therof, but when they weare come into his preſence: he ſharply rebuked them, and giuing them ſmall rewards, yet
<pb facs="tcp:173301:16"/> better then he thought them woorthy, he forbad them during their liues to come within xij. miles of the Court, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that vpon great penaltie. All theſe examples doo manifeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y prooue that liberall reward of vertue, and high and Honorable calling doo increaſe vertue in them in whome it is al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edy and cauſeth them in whom it is not ſaue only in appara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce, yet for pure ſhame to imbrace it, ſéeing that otherwiſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t coales are heaped vpon their heads, through their ſhameleſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes vnto them that haue ſo thorowly prouo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed them with the greatnes of their benefits.</p>
            <p>And therfore againſt all theſe reaſons and proof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to ſay that the Magiſtrate and Officer ſhould priuatly C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uet and conuert ſo great ſummes of treaſure: it were to ſhamefull and ſlaunderous, conſidered that they are the effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cauſes as hath already béen ſhewed And conſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red alſo the horrible and wicked concluſion that would enſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as alſo hath already béen prooued.</p>
            <p>Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) neuer tel me what might or dooth inſue therupon: but conſider the tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth and the matter as it is in déed. And if theſe great fées a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges doo not come vnto their receiuers and takers in proper and priuate: what meane they to make ſo great labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, ſute, fréendſhip and coſt to get thoſe offices and callings. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd how commeth it to paſſe that by the meanes of ſuch off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ces: ſuch as before were of ſmall habilitie, come to purcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons liuing, yea twaine or thrée. Shortly, that their care is greater to heare and learne where any Land or Lordſhip is to be ſolde: then for the Money whorwith to pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>haſe the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Simon confirmeth his aſſertion touching the deſire to beare office to be good, by the Ettimologia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the woord (Officium) Cap. 9.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:17"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoaſt) all theſe matters are eaſely deuided, vnto the which thus I anſwere. To the firſt which is their great deſire to be in ſuch Offices of receit, I ſay you miſ-iudge of their deſire becauſe you doo not vnderſtand the meaning of this woord Office and doo think him to be an Engliſhman wheras in very déed his Father is an <hi>Italian,</hi> whoſe proper ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and meaning you doo not vnderſtand, for in our Engliſh tung Office is no more to ſay nor nothing els but Seruice, ſo that whoſoeuer deſireth an Office hée deſireth to doo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice or els a place wherin to doo ſeruice, now all men knowe that a priuate man is not able to compare with the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate or Officer in abilitie and power. Therfore to deſire an Office is to deſire to be better abled, to expreſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the hart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e good wil and affection which hée hath to bée ſeruiceable vnto God and his common welth, for that in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat eſtate his power anſwereth not vnto his good will therin, and therfore the better man the more deſirous to be in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and in the more Offices, for the greater is his power to ſhew his good affection towards God who is the Giuer of all theſe things.</p>
            <p>¶ Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> I connot tel what Cun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie mans Office is, neither doo I greatly force whether his Father be an <hi>Italian, Spaniard</hi> or <hi>Frenchman,</hi> but if he be the ſame in <hi>Latin</hi> that ſeruice is in <hi>Engliſh:</hi> I am ſuer that both in <hi>Lattin, French, Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> hée ſtinketh when he is to fréely offered, and that (I am very ſure) did <hi>Aeſop</hi> mean in his Fable of the Sowe great with pig vnto whome (ſaith hée) there came a Fox who alleadging vnto her his great ſkil in the art of a Midwife profferd her his ſeruice toward her deliuerance, vnto whome ſhe anſwered, that the greateſt and beſt ſeruice that he could doo vnto her, was to kéep him far inough from her, which ſhée alſo praied him to doo, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may gather what the <hi>Authors</hi> opinion was vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this voluntary offer of ſeruice and yet hée dooth not alleadge that the Fox offered any money, I ſuppoſe becauſe hée had no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to offer. But <hi>Simon Magus</hi> offered money in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Acts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173301:17"/> Apoſtles, and what the holy Ghoſt thought therof: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou may there vnderſtand. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this is a colde reaſon and no Argument, to ſay that a mans earneſt deſire to haue an Office argueth his deſire of priuat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gaine &amp; proffit, and ſo for his great deſire to doo good: conde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me him of euil without proof therof. Neighboure <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) I doo not ſo barely reaſon, neither ſo nakedly as you haue alleaged if you did mée right in repetition of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not intercepting the ſame nor ſeuering the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ces ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of as you haue doon, and ſo haue anſwered the firſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt by it ſelf which is the weakeſt and haue ſaid nothing to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecond part which is their great purchaſe and the ſtrength &amp; effect of the firſt, for my Argument taken wholy togithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is thus much to ſay, that their great deſire to haue the Offices, and their great purchaſe of Landes and liuing following the ſame: ſheweth that from the beginning there was m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght els but priuate pouching, for euer the act that is laſt in exception: is the firſt in Imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all mens dooings this is moſte aſſured. Neighbour (quoth our Hoaſt) th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of yours which you holde ſo forcible is of no fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce at all whether the parties therof be conſidered ioyntly or ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uerally neither dooth this great deſire to be in Office, neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great purchaſe enſuing the ſame in any wiſe diſprooue my firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſertion and maintenaunce of this great reuenues, fées and charges as you ſuppoſe, conſtruing and taking m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaying to néer vnto the letter. For wheras I haue alle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ged the Magiſtrates and Officers to be the Patrons and Fathers of the common welth, and theſe great reuenues a publi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in their hands to the vſes and intents abooue r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herſed: yée alleadge againſt mée their great purchaſe of Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dſhips, Lands and Liuings as a repugnancie and diſpraiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therof, which it is not but the greateſt &amp; ſtrongeſt confirma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of that I my ſelf haue alleaged, for although I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e made them receiuers: yet haue I not charged them méerly as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers, but as baylifs &amp; Gardens of truſt whoſe authoritie extendeth to improoue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefit of their Cuntrie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But a better Improouement can there not be made, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring of money which is tranſitory: into land whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent,
<pb facs="tcp:173301:18"/> namely béeing deliuered vnto them at their yéers of diſcretion vpon the account of their ſaid Balifs or garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And euen as it fareth betwéen the Garden and his pupil, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bailifs and him to whoſe vſe he is put in truſt. So fareth it betwéen theſe Magiſtrates and Officers and the common welth as touching theſe receits.</p>
            <p>And therfore thoſe purchaſes of lands and poſſeſſions the beſt and moſte allowable diſcharge vpon their account that can poſſible be made vnto God, the greateſt and higheſt aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his honour and glory, the greateſt and moſte aſſured comfort and ſtay of his godly people and ſeruants vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the payment of the money from hand to hand had been but a temporall and a ſhort reléef, for euery man hath not the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ne right vſe therof, ſo ſlipper is it and fugitiue.</p>
            <p>But theſe Lands in the hands of theſe Landlords are a ſtay perpetuall and permanent wherunto the godly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perſon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſure of preferment and that for reaſon for why the Owners are ſuch in whome is no acceptaunce of Woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Fréendſhip, or of the greater offer, neither of other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g then vertue and godlines, and therfore their rent muſt néeds be eaſie, for who ſhould rate it by out bidding when the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly is no chapman neither dare preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him ſelf in the place for the godly perſon dooth it, no not vnto the wicked, much leſſe vnto his godly Brother or Neighbour. This is no ſmall commendation of Vertue and godlines and no ſmall encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement therto, namely where a man may make as ſuer &amp; a more ſure account of his Farme: then ſome other can make of their inheritaunce and patrimony. which thing although it ſéem ſtraunge: yet is it commonly verified in the Farmers of ſuch Landlords. For wée ſée to often that diuers honeſt and godly Men leaue their Inheritaunce vnto vngodly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftie Children (who falling into the hands of th'executor) doo little while inioy the ſame. The cauſe wherof is for that they came to their lands before they came to their Wit, and béeing Owners wared therby proude and in flatte béeing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no mans check and diſdaining al mens counſel and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting God and them ſelues fall to folly and then (as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) <hi>Their table is made a ſnare to take them
<pb facs="tcp:173301:18"/> and the things which ſhould haue been for their pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fit, are vnto them an occaſion of falling.</hi> So fearfull and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous is the ſinguler and ſole proprietie of great La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des and poſſeſſions, as that oftentimes it not only bereaueth the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of their right wit and Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: but alſo through their pride, vnthriftines and prodigallitie it hazardeth the ſincere adminiſtration &amp; execution of lawes and Iuſtice, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ocuring partialitie and fauour to vngodlynes and diſſolute liuing, whilſte they (whoſe dutie were to rebuke ſuch perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and to reſtraine their libertie) had rather enter into their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues and poſſeſſions and to take and vſe the oppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tunitie of their wickednes and retchleſnes as the méeteſt occaſion héerto. But in theſe Farmers and in their poſterit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is and that for the reuerend and honourable regarde between them and their Landlords at whoſe hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whoſe good wil and pleaſure they holde their liuings and whoſe great liberalitie and benignitie chargeth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m with no ſmall expectation aſwel of godly and honeſt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſation of life, as alſo of hoſpitalitie and charitable deali<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with their Bretheren and Neighbours béeing by their mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es very wel enabled therunto. Theſe things (I ſay) are l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oked for at their hands and that by them whoſe expectation they dare not nor cannot without great ſhame falſifie, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, thriftines and liberallitie in them is of no ſmall force to mooue others therunto, and ſo mutuall looue and charity che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed betwéen euery degrée, &amp; where theſe things are, God hath promiſed to bleſſe that houſe, Town, Cittie or Cuntry.</p>
            <p>It can hardly be ſpoken and much hardlyer wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ten how greatly and how mightely this procureth and ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aunceth Learning, Godlynes and Vertue, how much it fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thereth the deſire of contemplation and godly exerciſes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> minde, againſt which there is no Impediment nor hinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aunce ſo great as either the deſtitution or want of a compete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t liuing and maintenaunce, or els the dayly feare to be ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anted or diſappointed therof, and conſequently the thoughts and cares either to prouide for a competent liuing or els to maintaine and defend the ſame againſt the dayly Allarms and aſſaults of the Couetous and the vngodly againſt which the benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:173301:19"/> and goodnes of Owners and Landlords is the greateſt yea the only protection. Theſe are the effects and frutes of theſe purchaſes alleadged by you to be made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gains, fées and reuenues aforeſaid which doo far differ from the common purchaſing of other priuate perſons by whome (through your Ignoraunce or els of malice) you doo Iudge &amp; meaſure theſe which are nothing like nor comparable, as the effects and frutes therof will euidently declare, namely in the purchaſe of the Merchant, the Chapman, the Graſier, the clothier and ſuch other like Artificer what ſoeuer, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of all which perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s no ſuch thing is hoped or looked for. Firſt for that they doo not ſuſtaine any ſuch charge of expectation, neither is any reaſon that they ſhould, except a Shoomaker bying an Oxe hide for thrée ſhillings &amp; foure pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, might ſel ſhooes for twen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie ſhillings a paire: for that would alter the caſe. Therfore as his calling is baſe and mean: ſo is his iudgement as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Vertue and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Felicitie and end of mans life, which hée Iudgeth to conſiſt in getting and hauing, for that hée ſée'th men accounted and eſtéemed therafter, and other or farther Contemplation hath hée very little or none. So that in his Oppinion hée ſpéedeth his matters wunderfull wel if hée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn his Chaffer to his gain, &amp; the more and greater: ſo much the better, be it land or leaſe of Farme or houſe, if he can ſel it again for duble or treble that it coſt him or let it for thrée times the rent that hée payeth him ſelf for it. All this hée ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth honeſt gain and very wiſely handled, ſo that when he hath any thing to let or ſet, vp goeth the Drum &amp; as wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him the Deuil of hel, yea Belzabub him ſelfe as the Godlyeſt perſon in England, yea as an Angell of heauen, for godlynes, vertue or honeſtie is the laſt queſtion that hée wil aſke, only <hi>Quid vultis mihi daré?</hi> Thus is the godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſure to be put back or els to take the thing to his vtter detriment, ſo that vpon the matter no queſtion or difference whether of them ſpéed, for the euil man is made a great deale wurſſe, namely for that the greatnes of his rent ſtoppeth the mouth of him whoſe reduke hée ſhould moſte feare &amp; whome hée would and ſhould moſte reuerence and regarde, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wil hée be as wicked and as vngratious and corrupt as
<pb facs="tcp:173301:19"/> many others as hée can and dare for feare of the law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. The godly perſon although he gladly would doo good: yet wanteth hée power therto being ouer ſet with the greatnes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo that in concluſion whether the good or euil may ſpéed: they are forced to deale hardly with the world wherby a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſeth lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no amitie, fréendſhip or charitable looue, amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g men, but euen all for the peny as among méer Straunge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny zeale vnto God nor to doo any good for his ſake.</p>
            <p>By all theſe arguments, it appéereth manifeſtly h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w much it were to be wiſhed and deſired at the hands of Almightie God that only or chéefly ſuch were purchaſers &amp; La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d-lords whoſe very eſtates and callings and the manner of the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their gaines wherwith they purchaſe doo cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge them with a reuerend and fatherly regarde in letting and ſetting the ſame to the honor and glory of God who hath ſo mightely bleſſed them, yea ſo far abooue all that they euer co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld with out ſhame haue wiſhed or deſired, ſo heaping hot coales vpon their heads in their vnthankfulnes and dealing ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erwiſe, which (as I haue alredy ſaid) is not or at the leaſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be hoped or looked for at their hands of bace an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> meane calling. And therfore Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth hée) admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and confeſſing the greatnes of their purchaſe: y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t can yée not conclude againſt mée the proper or priuate rece t or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying of Charges, fées and reuenues aforeſaid ne ther wil I graunt it vnto you for the ſlaunderous and ſhame full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence which it inferreth neceſſarily as hath alr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ady béen duly prooued.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>‡ Pierce repeateth the Reaſons and Arguments of Simon and confuteth them by proof and expecience de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſe to the effect and that vpon his owne knowledge. Cap. 10.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:20"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>eighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) yée haue made as your ſelf dooth ſuppoſe many ſtrong reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to aprooue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt aſeſſing and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now receiui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of eight pence or twelue pence for a ſhéet of paper, and other exceſſiue and vnreaſonable Fées and charges of ſutes as not only tollerable, iuſt and reaſonable: but alſo godly and moſte conducible vnto the common welth, and to the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous and good eſtaſte therof, namely for that theſe fées and charges were ment and yet are the puniſhment of vice and the reward of godlynes and vertue. And alſo that they were and yet are ment a publique treaſure in the hands of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers therof, to all godly vſes, intents and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>Wherunto I anſwered, alleadging the great purchaſe of Lands and Lordſhips by the receiuers of the ſame as a thing repugnant and contrary to your Aſſertion, wherunto you haue replied that their great purchaſe is not only contrary to your firſt Aſſertion: but a confirmation of the ſame.</p>
            <p>For you ſay that their porchaſe of lands is a prouiſion with out compariſon more aſſured and permanent then were or could haue béen the diſtribution of the money or any parte therof from hand to hand, and alſo that the effects and fruits therof are moe and greater and doo ſtretch farther and more generally and vniuerſally doo procure the honor and glory of God, and the publique welth, peace and quietnes.</p>
            <p>To prooue that theſe things are ſo: you haue alleadged the honorable calling of the Magiſtrate and Officer, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great expectation that hée ſuſtaineth both before God and men, and alſo the reuerend opinion that we are bound to haue of him. Yée haue alſo alleadged that the firſt cauſes of all theſe great gaines and proffits are ſuch as of duty he is bound to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and not to proſecute, namely for that they are vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, wickednes and all kinde of vice, by the gain wherof (ſay you) no honeſt nor godly perſon can without great ſhame thriue and wax rich, much leſſe the Magiſtrate and Officer vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe great expectation héerin you doo ſo greatly inſiſt.</p>
            <p>Truely Neighbour (quoth hée) all theſe are goodly and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo godly reaſons and doo very wel prooue how things either
<pb facs="tcp:173301:20"/> haue béen or els how things ought to be.</p>
            <p>But that they are ſo preſently: theſe are either n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prooues at all or very ſmall and ſo your argument gathered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from <hi>poſſe</hi> to <hi>eſſe</hi> as I haue ſaid already, and as I wil further prooue by Arguments gathered from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cauſe vnto the effect and from the effect vnto the cauſe eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame that you haue alleadged, tying them together in the ſame maner and fourme as your ſelfe haue alleadge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them.</p>
            <p>Firſt you ſay that the originall cauſe of theſe gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t gains, Fées and reuenues was the hate that the firſt Aſſeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of bare vnto vngodlines, wickednes and all kinde of vice, the fauour and good affection which they bare vnto Vertue, and godlynes, and therin they ment the puniſhme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the one and the preferment and aduauncement of the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her, and ſo you conclude lewdnes, vnthriftines and vngodlynes to haue béen and yet ſtil to be the firſt cauſe of theſe great gains, Fées and reuenues, and theſe great Fées and reuenues their effect, the effect of theſe fées, profits and reuenues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ée haue alleadged or rather I my ſelf haue alleadged, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou haue confeſſed and iuſtified to be the great perpuiſition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of Lordſhips, lands and poſſeſſions by the Magiſtrates and Officers Receiuers of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The effect of their great purchaſe is by you ale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dged to be a prouiſion, a ſtay of liuing and patry mony for the Godly and honeſt People of the common welth, and for their aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, peace and quietnes. The effect of ſo good a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouiſion for the Godly: you haue alleadged to be the increaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f them, and the decreaſe of the wicked, vnthriftie and vngodly, the effect of the increaſe of godly people you haue alleadged to be mutuall looue &amp; charitie and all good affection both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owards God and alſo one to an other, the effect wherof you haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged to be the manifolde bleſſings of God accordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g to the ſaying of the Prophet in the hundred thrée &amp; thirtie <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue you argued from the firſt cauſes pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ducing their effects, and from thoſe effects as from cauſes of their ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fects very orderly and very probablie, but not nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſarilye as I haue already alleadged, and as I doubt not héerafter
<pb facs="tcp:173301:21"/> I ſhall prooue vnto you ſo directly and ſo euidently that you ſhall either confeſſe your owne prooues fallible and falſe: or els you muſt and ſhal ſay that cauſes produce no effects or els clean contrary effects, which is to reuerſe and to ouerthrowe the order of Nature and all the law and rule of reaſon as to ſay there can be a Father or a mother without a Sonne or a Daughter or that betwéen a man or a woman there ſhould be begotten a dogge or a cat. And for proof héerof I wil aleage bothe reaſon as ſtrong as you haue alleaged any: and alſo mine owne experience which I my ſelf haue déerly bought and paid for. I pray you Neighbour let mée héer that (quoth our Hoaſt).</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Pierce Plowmans firſt tale for that purpoſe where he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth how his Neighbour and hee went to the Tauern and to the daunſing Schoole and what hapned there. Chap. 12.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T my béeing in London this laſt term (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) it fortuned one afternoone haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g little or nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to doo, as God knoweth what Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; vngodlines commeth of our idle waiti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; attending vpon our dayes of heari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as they tearm them, when in the mean time we run vp and down in the ſtréets, and if happely wée méet with any Fréend or acquaintaunce: it is holden great humanitie to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him the curteſie of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is as much to ſay to haue him to the Tauern &amp; there to ſit bibbing vntil neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſcant finde the way foorth again. So as I was about to tel you, one day amongſt all others wée met a company of Neighbours and Fréends together in Poules, ſix in number all Cuntrie-men and Neighbours, ſaue one that was a Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doner a Neighbour borne of ours, who was our Leader to many a good place dout you not, ſo on Gods name néeds wée muſt to the Tauern, and ſo wée went to the Tauern, there faſt by, wherby that time we came forth again: our heds were better laden with heare then with Wit, ſo on Gods name
<pb facs="tcp:173301:21"/> when our heds were wel fraughted: wée muſt née<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s go to ſée ſome pleaſures of the Cittie that were ſtraunge an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> noueltie vnto vs of the Cuntrie, and ſo on Gods name wée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent into a dauncing Schoole not very far thence, now was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here one man of our Company that was as deaf as a doore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ile.</p>
            <p>¶ When wée weare come into the Schoole: the Muſitions were playing and one dauncing of a Galiard, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> euen at our entring hée was beginning a trick as I remem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téens or ſeuentéens, I doo not very wel reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hée leaped, flung and took on, which the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, and not hearing any noyſe of the Muſic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, thought verily that hée had béen ſtark mad and out of his wit, and of pure pittie and compaſſion ran to him and caught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im in his armes and held him hard and faſt. The Dauncer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his good meaning and taking it to the wurſt, and hauing a Dagger drew it out and ſmot the man a great bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>we vpon the hed, and brake his hed very ſore.</p>
            <p>The man ſore mooued and gréeued therewitha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, and bée<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing a man of great ſtrength: threw him from hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with all his ſtrength among the Muſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and hee lighting vpon one of the greateſt and faireſt Vialls, brake it all in pée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es.</p>
            <p>Therwithal vp ſtart the Muſitions for him and we for to help the other béeing our Fréends and Neighbours and then went out Daggers, vp went Pantoſtes, al the reſt of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in the throng were all to trodden and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roken, and but that Neighbours hearing the noiſe and bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>li<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g came in and parted vs: ſurely ſome of vs had béen in grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> daunger to haue béen ſlain.</p>
            <p>I loſt my Cloake and had my hed broken and ſo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d thrée of my Neighbours moe, and hardly the Muſitions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd their partakers went not ſcotfrée. But ſhortly to end a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> come to my purpoſe: you ſhall heare what followed.</p>
            <p>Firſt and formoſte wée were all arreſted and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmitted to Priſon for a fraie and bloodſhed, where I think you may make no queſtion if it coſt vs any thing before w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> gat out again. But hauing paid our Fées there, and thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the wurſt had béen paſt: euen at our comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng foorth from thence wée were all newly arreſted by latita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mained
<pb facs="tcp:173301:22"/> vntil wée had put in Sureties to appéer at the day of the return of the writ in the Kings bench. So wée laid our purſes togither and went to a woorſhipful and learned Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer that had béen of our counſaile aforetime, and ſhewed him the declarations that were againſt vs, wherof the firſt was at the ſute of the Owner of the ſchoole, wherin hée alleadged that with force and armes wee had entred into his houſe and beaten, wounded and euil intreated his Seruants, by reaſon wherof he had loſt their ſeruice by the ſpace of eight dayes, to his hinderaunce and damage ſix pound, and alſo then and their thrée Inſtruments of Muſick commonly called Vialls did ſpoile and break to his loſſe and hinderaunce ſix pound.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, euery of his Seruants the parties the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ſeuerally declared againſt vs all ioyntly of an aſſault and bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tery made vpon them, and that wée had beaten, wounded and euil intreated them to their ſeuerall damages fortipence, the Dauncer himſelf declared ſeuerally againſt the deaf man for aſſaults and battery, vpon all which matters wée praied his counſel and aduice, his anſwer was ſhortly that in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the law was againſt vs in all and euery of our caſes wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of he gaue vs the cauſes &amp; reaſons as I ſhal reherſe vnto you.</p>
            <p>To the firſt point of the firſt declaration for forcible entry wée praied his reaſon, how or by what reaſon our entrie mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght be ſaid forcible ſéeing the doores were open, and if they had béen ſhut our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in was but to hear &amp; ſée, &amp; our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning not hurtfull to any man. His anſwere therunto was that a mans meaning that commeth into my houſe ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued and taken to haue béen ſuch from the beginning as is his act there doon after he is entred, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe taken for his meaning &amp; the declaration therof, namely where hée entreth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſpecial commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the party, &amp; becauſe (ſaith hée) that after your entry into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe yée did there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a force &amp; vnlawful act: therfore your firſt entry and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the houſe ſhalbe déemed &amp; iudged vnlawful &amp; forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Then we aſked how or by what reaſon our act could bée ſaid vnlawful which was but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> taking of a man in his armes of very good wil to ſtay him thinking that he had béen mad &amp; out of his wit and might haue miſcheiued him ſelf. His an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb facs="tcp:173301:22"/> therunto was that therin the act was not lawfull nor iuſticiable but a Treſpaſſers although no farther h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rme had enſued therupon, which yet (by your confeſſion) the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e did for to ſpeak generally: it is not lawful to imbrace or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rain any man againſt his wil, for if him liſt to take it to the burſt (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if there inſue any euil vnto the partie ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y) it ſhall not help the party to ſay that hée ment him good or it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt no euil therby, for although that in felony the inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t doo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the fact it is not ſo in Treſpaſſers wherfore your act was not lawful nor Iuſticiable except yée had béen Officers or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yée had come in &amp; found the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dooing ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elonious or vnlawful act, by means wherof yée had had ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ient coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to haue laid your hands vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for euery man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer for peace ſake &amp; for the preſeruation therof, &amp; then (quoth hée) your caſe had béen otherwiſe, vnto this wée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwered that our act in all reaſon ſéemed more lawfull and tollerable then theirs, for that in their exerciſe there is little good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or none at all, nor better end or purpoſe then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o induce ſuch euil and vnhappy euents and conſequents as hapned in this caſe of ours, and that therfore their cauſe oug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t not to haue fauour againſt vs as if we had hindered or interrupted their honeſt or lawful exerciſe in any godlines or in any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tending vnto vertue, to the glory of God, or to the proffit of the common wealth. His anſwere vnto that was that we are not to diſpute of that which the reuerend and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>norable Magiſtrates haue eſtabliſhed yea &amp; holden in no ſmall repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it falleth for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrates, Rulers &amp; Officers to beare with them in all incidents &amp; caſualties otherwiſe ſhould they diſſalow their owne Acts and be contrary vnto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſelues, which were inconuenient. Then wée demaunde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of him why for the firſt Viall that was broken: the Maiſter ſhould not bring the action againſt the Dauncer who in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery déed was the breaker therof, and not the other man. His anſwere therunto was that in very déed wée were both Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpaſſers vnto him alike, &amp; he at his libertie &amp; election to take his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt vs both or againſt any of vs for (quoth hée) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dauncer were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> material cauſe yet was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> efficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe therof, as for proof, if a carter wilfully driu his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art
<pb facs="tcp:173301:23"/> ouer a man, woman or Childe, bothe the Cart, the Horſes, and the Carter are guiltie of the fact wherof the deaf man is not excuſeable neither can plead not guiltie to the fact, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hée was the firſt and chéef efficient cauſe, therupon wée mooued vnto him this queſtion, why the Muſitians them ſelues ſhould not be ſaid to be the firſt efficient cauſe ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> without their noiſe the Dauncer would not ſo haue fared nor taken on, neither the deaf man haue taken him for a madde man, as bothe you and wée would haue doon if wée had béen in his caſe, and had heard no more then hée heard.</p>
            <p>Vnto that his anſwere was, that whatſoeuer it ſéemed vnto him or vnto vs, it is (quoth hée) at your peril, and at all mens perils els that reſorte and hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſuch places to put on all our Sences, wits and vnderſtandings, and alſo to deſire God to giue them wiſdome and his grace to Iudge wiſely &amp; wel to digeſt ſuch things as they heare and ſée therin, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wée be not ſnared in euil through ignorant appetite of our ſences vnto our hinderaunces more then wée our ſelues are able of our ſelues to Iudge or think, for (ſaith hée) ſéeing wée are not able, neither is our authoritie to blame or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the places, neither to diſalowe the things there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, which were to derogate from the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Yet if wée haue ſo much grace of God as to the Magiſtrates vnto our ſelues and in ſuch caſes to blame and reprooue our ſelues, and our owne ſences, and inordinate deſires, either in due time before wée are fallen, or els in ſome reaſonable time, and with our reaſonable loſſe and hinderaunce it may ſuffice for anſwere vnto vs by them vnto whome otherwiſe wée muſt créep and pray our redreſſe neither able to craue it at their hands without an inconuenience aforeſaid, which is condemne and diſalowe the things by them ſelues allowed and eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Wée aſked him what reaſon there was that wée ſhould be charged in ſeuerall actions and vnto ſeuerall perſons, for one treſpaſſe, as namely vnto the Maiſter and alſo to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. His anſwere therunto was that the Maiſter hath a ſpeciall intereſt in his ſeruant for the proffit hée is to receiue by his ſeruice for which ſeruice hée is to recouer &amp; not for the
<pb facs="tcp:173301:23"/> hurt doon vnto the perſon for the partie him ſelfe recouereth for that. To be ſhort, his reſolution was that for all our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and loſſe that we had gotten: wée were ſo farre from all hope of redreſſe or amends, that wée were in the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſſe caſe in our defence againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; very like to yéeld ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of law. And thus you ſée (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) how po re guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe &amp; ſimple men in a far honeſter cauſe are put to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wurſer end. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoaſt) as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, be as bée may. But truly Neighbour you had but euil ſucce ſe in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſée pleaſure and to heare Muſick, and yet tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt mée if yée wil, I ſuppoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſped a great deale better th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſpéed in ſuch like places, who think neuerthel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe them ſelues to haue ſped there wel, and come away righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, which in very déed is the only cauſe why i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie they ſpéed wurſe then you, for why you are hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and féel it, but they are hurt but haue no féeling therof v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>til their hurt be paſt all cure, for a man is neuer ſo daunge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſly ſick or ſore as when hée hath loſt the ſence and féeling o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſore or of the ſicknes. So fareth it in ſuch perſons as theſe, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they féel no euil that they contract, and yet in ſuch places, yet doo they carry thence with them the ſéeds and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical cauſes of great infortunes as the wofull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble end of many a good mans Childe hath witneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d dayly, dooth and wil. But truly Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Hoaſt) you are waxen more then half a Lawyer by theſe meanes.</p>
            <p>Nay ſoft (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) I haue an other matter to tel you and that almoſte as ſtraunge as this, and that chaunced to my ſelfe in a miſchaunce about a foure yéers paſt, I pray yée let vs heare it quoth our Hoaſt, mary quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> thus it hapned. A fréend of mine would néeds giue mée my din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at an Ordinary table where wée fared very dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tely, but I promiſe you for mine owne parte I haue though my ſelf better at eaſe many a time &amp; oft with bread &amp; chéeſe in other Company. So Sir in the name of God when di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ner was doon: in ſtéed of grace to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dice they went on euery ſide vpon proper ſquare tables fit I warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you for the purpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; there to the hazard they go xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xl. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v. l. vi. l. a caſt, I ſtood by and beheld. Anon there came a ſtraunger a plain homely fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb facs="tcp:173301:24"/> of the Cuntrye much like my ſelf and hée ſéeing ſuch ſummes of money vpon the boord, &amp; the dice trotting to and fro and that now one ſnatched a heap and now an other ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and heap, and therwithall ſuch deuout ſwearing, he came to mée and rounding me in the eare, aſked me whoſe weare all thoſe heaps of money that were laid foorth, mary (quoth I) his that can get them, get them (quoth hée) how? Marry (quoth I) by hazard, ſay you ſo (quoth hée) claime they no farther propertie in their money but by hazard whether themſelues ſhall haue their money or an other man? no veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (quoth I) What are thoſe white things ful of black ſpots that are ſo chaſed to and fro? Thoſe (quoth I) are called dice vpon whome ſtandeth the hazard, and therwithal my Fréend and I hauing dined and diſpatched: went our way foorth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Temple, and before we had gon ſo farre as a man might ſhoot a Bird bolte: there aroſe an outcry behinde vs, ſtop the théef, ſtop the théef, and therwithall I looked behinde mée: and loe the fellowe of whome I tolde you, came running with both his hands ful of money and after him ran the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Ordinary and thrée or foure of his ſeruants as faſt as euer they could run with hue and cry, we turned not back neither made vs to doo therin. So they followed him vntil they came as farre as Saint Dunſtones Church, and there the fellowe being out of breath, turned again and catching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maiſter of the dicing houſe in his armes: cryed I haue him I haue him, this is the théef (quoth hée) Now was the throng ſo great y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man could not know which was which vntil at the laſt the Officers came and took them bothe and knowing the Maiſter of the dicing houſe: aſked him what the matter was.</p>
            <p>Mary (quoth hée) this Villain Théef hath robbed diuers Men of Woorſhip my Gueſts of great ſummes of money and I haue followed him for he fled vpon the fellony. And there hée had ſpied mée in the Company &amp; bad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay hold vpon me for this knaue (quoth he) gaue him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel &amp; is as falſe a théef as hée. There was no more to ſay, I was laid hold vpon &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and bothe hée and I caried before a Iuſticer of peace the fellow and I, my fréend would not leaue mée but went with mée to ſée and heare the end. So ſir, when wée
<pb facs="tcp:173301:24"/> were come before the Iuſticer: hée laid ſore to the Fellowes charge that hée had broken his houſe forciblie and burglarlie and had felloniouſly robbed foure Gentlemen of wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſhip his Gueſts of diuers ſummes of money feloniouſly an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt the Quéens lawes and peace. Sirra (quoth the Iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice) what ſaiſt thou to this? Sir quoth the fellowe I beſeech y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my good Fréend and Maiſter and let mée haue but law &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at your hands, I truſt it appéereth vnto your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcretion (quoth hée) that this matter alleadged againſt mée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to put me to anſwere therunto. Firſt for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible entrie into his houſe and burglarye ſuppoſed: I ſay his houſe was open, and dayly is and to long hath béen and vnto to many if it pleaſed God and the Maieſtrates ſuch as your Woorſhip is, for I vndertake hée that hath any thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g to loſe and caſt away: néed neither break doore nor walle t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leaue it behinde him there, and ſo much for my anſwere vnto that part. As to the money ſuppoſed to be ſtolne: hée declareth no certaintie therof, neither conueieth to him ſelf any property therin, and ſo no fellony of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing wherto no man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laimeth propertie, very true it is (quoth hée) that I came into his houſe and ſéeing a company ſtanding about a ſquare Table &amp; diuers great heaps of money laid foorth therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I aſked this honeſt man that was a ſtander by meaning (mée) what was ment thereby, and alſo by two white ſquare things full of black ſpots that were chaſed to and fro vpon the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rd, hée anſwered mée that they were playing at the dice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r that is quoth he the name of thoſe ſquare bones, and ſaid farther that the name of their game was hazard. When I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d heard him ſay ſo: I conſidered with my ſelf that there mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be good to be doon for me among them, for hauing wel mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed their order: I found them the moſte indifferent People t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gain by that euer I met withall in my life, for I perceiued that hée that laid the money downe: the reſt meant that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhould neuer take it vp again, and for his parte hée me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t aſwell vnto them and that all this ſtood in the fauour of haz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd, and ſo often time it chaunced accordingly, to wit that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> box bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the third perſon: caught a ſhare and by no other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or better title then mée thought my ſelf to haue, for me thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t I was
<pb facs="tcp:173301:25"/> as indifferent to euery of them as was the box or as any of them was to other, for I verily thought and yet doo that if nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of them euer fingered that laid down either had his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire againſt other, moreouer quoth hée, when I beheld ſuch lewd and ſhameful miſpending of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, ſuch horrible ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and blaſpheming &amp; knew not where neither vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to complain for reformation therof and thought in conſcience I ought not to ſuffer it as far foorth as it were in my might &amp; I ſaw no way ſo likely to redreſſe it as to take away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe which I perceiued was the money. I thought that both by law and good conſcience I might doo it and ought alſo, and in this deliberation I awaighted my time &amp; ſnatched vp al that I could lay holde vpon and came my way, wherupon I pray your diſcretion and whether this be fellony wherin there is title or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt cullour of title. A Sirra quoth the Iuſticer, you are acu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning théef indéed, it is time to look to ſuch knaues as you are. Sir quoth the poor fellowe, I beſéech you be good to me, I am a poore man and I truſt, ſauing againſt them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loſt the money the money is mine againſt all men and as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them when they demaund me: let me anſwere. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching that honeſt man quoth heby me, I neuer delt with him nor neuer ſaw him before, to be ſhort the Fellowe was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Newgate, and I was fain to finde ſurety by recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſaunce to appéer at the next ſeſſions there to make anſwere to ſuch matter as ſhould then and there be laid to my charge and that coſt me fiue ſhillings and this was all that I got by hauing my dinner giuen mée.</p>
            <p>And what ſaid your Lawyer to you for this ſaid our Hoaſt, what comfort dooth he giue you of a mendes againſt the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that thus miſuſed you, truely (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) hée vtterly diſcourageth mée to ſtur or meddle farther therin, and all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame reaſons that hée made before or els the very like in effect. Truely Neighbour quoth our Hoaſt, that Lawyer was no Counceller neither for your purpoſe and much leſſe for his owne. Why ſo Neighbour (quoth <hi>Pierce?</hi>) marry quoth our Hoaſt, for there is no courage in him neither hath he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> way to help him ſelf, &amp; to kéep you in dooing, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he giueth ſuch cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel to peace and quietnes, vnto ſuch fellowes as you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173301:25"/> would gladly cut him out woork if hmſelf were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is owne hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Nay ſurely Neighbour ꝙ <hi>Pierce,</hi> wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> counſel ſoeuer he had geuen me therin, or what counſel he or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them all ſhall héerafter giue me in ſuch matters: I am taught alredy though to my coſt, while I liue to loue peace &amp; enſue it, &amp; to looue mine owne houſe, my honeſt lab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel and chéefly &amp; aboue all other things to ſerue Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wherin I finde the only ſtay and comfort of mans life to reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; that when all is ſought and tried: there is none other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le ne le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel wel and ſurely to guid and order our affairs an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dooings.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>The application of Pierces tale by the Hoſte, tha the great charges of the Law is profitable to the commonwelth, and a repreſſing of vice and ſinne. Cap 13.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ha, very wel ſaid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (quoth our Hoſte) I am glad y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yet at the laſt ye are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unto I haue al this while laboured to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you which is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe great and exceſſiue charges &amp; expences haue reformed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> changed you from an vngodly and troubleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me man: to a Godly, wiſe and prudent man, able to giue co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſell not only priuatly and to your owne fréends and famely: but alſo to beare office and authoritie in your Parriſh, yée i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Shire where we both dwell, ſo that I hope from hencefoorth we ſhall haue great ſtore of you, and that of the greatnes of ſuch fées and charges of ſutes in Law, and of the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors and the now receiuers therof ye are vtterly co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cluded &amp; eſtopped to ſpeak or think ſaue in all honor &amp; reue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence. Doo you think ſo Neighbour (quoth he?) Yea verily quoth he, for you haue confeſſed all this your reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endment to haue commen thence, and look what effect it hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wrought in you: ye are of charitie bound to think that it hath wrought, woorketh &amp; wil woork in a number mo then you, and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that you haue or rather think that haue departe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from: is in their hands who are treaſurers therof, as I haue aleaged towards the good and godly vſes, intents &amp; purpoſes that may or ſhall ariſe héerafter in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon benefit, to wit, ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice of the whole common welth, wherin your part is as farr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> foorth as theirs. Doo you call this a mending Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth
<pb facs="tcp:173301:26"/> 
               <hi>Pierce?</hi> In very déed quoth he, I muſt néeds confeſſe, that theſe great and exceſſiue Charges and large Expences haue rebuked me, haue chaſticed and amended me, but to ſay that I think or iudge it thank woorthy vnto them that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued my money: I ſay the Deuil kiſſe his arſſe that ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth me or any fréend of mine, for verily ſuch amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in my iudgement, deſerueth aſmuch and the very like thanks as did the Wife, who gaue her huſband two ſtrong poiſons, meaning to ſpéed him in déed, but the poyſons bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of contrary natures: wrought one vpon an other, and deſtroyed either others force, wherby the man béeing hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled for a ſeaſon, yet béeing driuen into a laſk by their extremitie: auoyded them bothe and with them much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ſo that where before he was a very corrupt body: he was by their clenſings the better xx. yéers after. Thus ſhe did him good by accident, but far from her intent or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and vtterly againſt her will. And ſurely they that take ſo exceſſiuely of me and of others our money, &amp; by that kinde of puniſhment amend and refourme vs: I holde them woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as much thank therfore as was this Wife at her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands hand for his amendment which was wrought by her meane. For I dare ſafely vndertake, that for our affliction and puniſhment, or for the diſhonour of God and other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlynes that dependeth therupon: they are as ſorowful as was the pariſh Clark of a Town that was ſore viſited with the Plague, who ſaid vnto his wife vpon a day. Wife (quoth he) if there come two corpſes to day: we will haue a ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Mutton and a quart of Sack to ſupper, &amp; if there come but one: wée will haue a ſhoulder of Mutton and but a pinte of Sack. Content huſband (quoth ſhe) And verily I think that as hartely as this good man &amp; his Wife praied for their recouery that were viſited: ſo hartely pray theſe for peace, quietnes and the honor and ſeruice of God, and the Godly &amp; charitable dealing and liuing of their Neighbours and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>Pierce prooueth that the ſufferaunce of wickednes and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes increaſeth their gaine who are and ſhould be therebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and puniſhers therof, and that to be the cauſe of great
<pb facs="tcp:173301:26"/> in iuſtice and vnrighteouſnes. Cap. 14.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte) I pray you let me further vnderſtand w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at yée doo meane by this hiſtory, for it ſhould ſéem that ye haue alleadged it againſt mee not with ſtanding that it maketh for me by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he wun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effect which you your ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re forced to confeſſe, that it hath wrought vpon you. I kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>we what I haue confeſſed Neighbour (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) and alſo in what maner I haue confeſſed it, far enough from your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urpoſe or any confirmation therof. And where in maintenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of theſe great fées and reuenues you haue alleaged that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and alſo how many and how good &amp; godly are the'ffects and fruits therof: without proof made of them or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any one of them, either by your owne experience or by oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry demonſtration. There in proof of the contrary t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wit, that they are proper and priuate, and therfore exceſſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable which is my aſſertion, I haue brought you this proffe of mine owne experience, wherby I haue ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fficiently ſhewed that the firſt cauſes of all theſe great gaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits are proſecuted as I haue affirmed and not per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecuted as you pretend. For I haue partely ſhewed you héer what leaue and libertie the common people namely youth haue to follow their own luſt and deſire, in all wantonnes and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſolution of life. For further proof wherof: I call to witneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aters, Curtines, Heauing houſes, Rifling boothes, Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alleyes and ſuch places where the time is ſo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amefully miſpent, namely the Sabaoth daies vnto the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhonor of God, and the corruption and vtter diſtruction of youth. All which (I ſay) are either the cauſes or the effec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of theſe great gaines and reuenues, or els both cauſes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d effects interchaungeably. For I dare vndertake that if eit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er theſe gains and profits were publique as you pretend, or els if there were as great gain and proffit to the Maieſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ates and Officers, in the godly liues and honeſt conuerſation of the common people as there is in the contrary: theſe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bours of vngodlines &amp; miſnurture, would haue leſſe fauour and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce
<pb facs="tcp:173301:27"/> then they haue, and godlines, Sobrietie and modeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of liues &amp; maners: would be in greater eſtimation then they are, and the honor and glory of God more aduaunced therby. But alas that the honor and glory of God and the vaine glory, pompe and maieſtie of man cannot ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt néeds fall in the others exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for certainly the more libertie vnto wickednes &amp; ſinne and the more falling from God through the ſame: and the more humbly complainings vnto your good Lordſhips, and vnto your good Woorſhips. The more Recognances for the peace and good a bearing, aſwel by the Godly as by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, the one inuading and the other defending: the more praying, paying, waiting, attending, dowking, crowding, &amp; courteſing, procuring of fréendſhip by meanes, bribing of his flatterer, &amp; bribing of her flatterer, this driueth the great welth and abundance into few mens hands. For where, the vngodly through miſgouerment is fallen into daunger of the Law, what wil he not giue to redéem his life or his infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye? yea euen vnto them who were the firſt cauſes and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of his fall into ſuch folly and miſchaunce through li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie and not reſtraint of the contempt of God, his Lawes, and ſeruice, which he will not fayle to meaſure and fully to reward vnto all libertines, contemners and deſpiſers of his maieſtie and will, giuen them ouer into a reprobate minde, from vice to vice, vntil he hath fully brought him to naught.</p>
            <p>So dangerous and fearfull a thing is libertie and not reſtraint of the beginning of euil, which although they appéer not ſuch at the firſt: yet when they are come to their ripenes and haue brought foorth their increaſe, to wit, Fellonyes, Thefts, Man ſlaughter, Murder and ſuch like: there is not ſo ignorant a perſon that will not ſay, the man or woman was neuer like to come to better end, namely for his euil and diſſolute life in the beginning.</p>
            <p>This libertie is in the hands of Maieſtrates and Officers to bid or to forbid, euen after as they will prefer the honor and glory of God, or els their owne welth, pomp and vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory. And therfore how hartely were it to be deſired at the hands of GOD, that ſuch as are Maieſtrates and Officers:
<pb facs="tcp:173301:27"/> ſhould not be couetuoꝰ, or els ſuch as are couetoꝰ ſhould not be Magiſtrates, for héerof <hi>Iethro</hi> did warne <hi>Moyſes</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xviij. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> talking with him concerning the election and choiſe of Maieſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Officers, and bad him chuſe ſuch as hated couatiſe, and ſpake of no other vice. The cauſe whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>of is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, to wit leaſt the wickednes and vngodlines of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple came to be valuable let and ſet, rented and far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght and ſolde, for what other thing is valluing, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting and ſetting, renting, buying and ſelling of offices whoſe value is more or leſſe according to the ſtate of the people and their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honouring of God therby. And where you maint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine theſe great gains by their godly and woorthy effects, the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you alleadge to be their great purchaſe of lordſhips, lands and poſſeſſions and the effect therof you alleadge to be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion and patrimony for the good and godly, the ef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of yée ſay is the increaſe of them, and the decreaſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the effect wherof you ſay is godlines, vnanimitie, loue, charetie and benignitie one towards an other. And laſt of all the effect therof be the manifold graces and bleſſings of God promiſed by God in the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> to the houſe, town Cittie or Cuntry where theſe things are. From the firſt cauſe to his ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect I graunt your argument, that theſe great gains are cauſe of great purchaſe, but from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purchaſe to his effects yée ſhew not how it is: but how it ought to be, for inſtéed of the effects wherof you haue ſpoken, I ſée many gay houſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul of gay ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>is, coſtly banqueting houſes, Galleries, bowling Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is, ſtrange toies of point deuiſe and woorkmanſhip, but with in I finde no man dwelling ſaue pride, who hath ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hoſpitalitie and charitie, and as for other preferment that the godly haue at their hands in any of their purchaſes: I ſée not but euen who wil giue moſte, and can make might<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who thoſe are in our daies: the vngodly, vnfai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hfull and vncharitable dealing ſo vniuerſally doo plainly decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re.</p>
            <p>The people ſo euel giuen both yong and olde, ſo vngodly in li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing ſo vnciuil, yea ſo rude &amp; barbarous in manners, wherin me thinketh they haue preuailed &amp; increaſed more &amp; more all after as theſe offices haue waxen more gainfull and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire
<pb facs="tcp:173301:28"/> to haue them greater. And therfore your diſtinction betwéen their purchaſe and the merchant, chapman, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> perſons what ſoeuer (ſauing his probabilitie) vain and redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to the purpoſe. Therfore Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) your reaſons are weak &amp; to maintain the greatnes of their fées vnable. Abide Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoaſte, giue me leaue to anſwere vnto theſe matters, &amp; firſt becauſe that in very déed probable reaſon giueth place to neceſſary proof &amp; demonſtration, wherin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſuppoſe that ye haue you be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yond me, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> againſt my b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e &amp; naked reaſons as you terme them, ye haue alleadged authoritie, and that of your owne experience. I wil anſwere you with the like, and that of mine owne experience alſo, and more direct vnto my mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any of yours, which are indéed indirect and ſtand in different, and I wil pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that the Magiſtrate and Officer in the beginning was and yet is ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I haue aleadged and alſo the firſt aſſeſſing of the ſaid fées and reuenues, and their great vtillitie and neceſſitie, namely for the vſes, intents and purpoſes aforeſaid. For proof wherof I wil rehearſe vnto you a matter which I my ſelf did bothe heare and ſée.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>The Hoſte maintaineth the contrary, and for diſproofe therof, and for the proofe of his aſſertion: alleadgeth the purchaſe of a certain welthie Officer towards the Law. Chap. 15.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout two yeeres agon it was m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fortune to be beyond London in <hi>Kent,</hi> at the houſe of a worſhipfull Officer towards the Law, who not p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt a Moneth before my comming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: had purchaſed a Lordſhip, wherin were diuers good forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and their leaſes too expire at Miche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to come twelue Moneths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It came to paſſe one day of my béeing there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thither came a rich man dwelling not farre thence, whoſe ſute was to this Gentleman to take one of his ſaid Farmes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euertion, and comming to him thus he began. Sir quoth he, I vnderſtand ye haue bought ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h a Lordſhip, God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne ye joy thereof. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:173301:28"/> true it is (quoth hée) Sir ꝙ this rich man, I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay you let me be your tenaunt of ſuch a Farm, geuing more then any o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther man wil giue for a fine. The rent of the Farm was v. l.</p>
            <p>What will ye giue me for a leaſe for xxj. yéeres quoth this Gentleman? Sir quoth he I wil giue ye an C.l. and vnto our Miſtreſſe a Veluet gown, and xx. Angels to buy h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r pines be ſides. You haue bidden like a Chapman ſaid the Gentleman, giue me leaue to be aduiſed vnto Munday next ſaid he, and then I ſhall giue you an anſwere héerin, ſo cauſing him to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dinner he let him departe, and this was vpon a Thurſday</p>
            <p>The next day béeing Friday: this Gentleman ſent for the Farmer of the ſame péece of land, who came thither, and with him thrée hanſome yong men his ſonnes. So when he was by the Landlords commaundement brought befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him: hée aſked him of what age he was. He anſwered lxxv. yéeres. He aſked him how long he had dwelled in that Farm He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red that he had dwelt there all his life for he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orne in it and his father before him. You know quoth the Gentleman that I am now become your Landlord. I knowe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very wel quoth he, and I beſéech you of your fauour. What will you giue for a new leaſe of xxi. yéeres quoth the Gentleman? for you knowe your olde leaſe is néer an end. Sir quoth the poore man, let me giue you reaſon, only that I may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble to doo my Prince and your woorſhip ſeruice, &amp; to reléeue my poore neighbours as hetherto I haue doone, and haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Very wel quoth the Gentleman, be héer again vpon Munday next and then ye ſhall vnderſtand more. The poore man (his duty doon) departed. The next Munday beeing mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day next before <hi>Bartholmew</hi> day: the poore man was come again, and brought with him a couple of fat Capons, &amp; about an houre or twaine after came this Churle very wel moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Gelding not déere of x.l. and behinde him was truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a fat Buck, which he preſented vnto the Gentlemen by one of his ſeruants. To be ſhort: he was willed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o come in to the M. into a cloſe little Parlor, whether were called alſo this olde farmer and I my ſelf, whom it pleaſed hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to vouch ſafe all curteſie and humanitie both in this and alſo in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:173301:29"/> matters, ſo that only we foure were there, ſauing a yong man attendant vpon his perſon. This doon: the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman began fréend quoth he, what accuſation doo you bring againſt this poore man pointing him to the Farmer. Sir ꝙ. he none, I doo not know the man. No quoth the Gentleman? except ye can accuſe him of euel: ye haue already condemned your ſelf therof, and would doo me. Why ſo ſir quoth he? Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sir quoth the Gentleman, for he cannot be guiltleſſe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil: that ſéeketh the deſtruction and death of a guiltleſſe man.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth the fellowe, ye charge me wrongfully, I neuer ſought any mans death. Sir quoth the Gentleman, he that ſéeketh to take away the ſuſtenaunce of a mans life, that man ſay I, ſéeketh his death, &amp; that by ſo much a more cruel mean as it is a more cruell and fearfull death, to ſtarue of hunger or colde: then it is to be quickly and readily diſpatched and murthered, and ſo ſoon rid out of pain. Ye haue quoth hée, deſired to take this poore mans farme from him, béeing his only ſtay, and haue ſo bidden for it: that I know he may not liue but in extreme miſery if he take it at your hands. Sir ꝙ. he, yée are the firſt great purchaſer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer I heard of this opinion. I haue ſix Farmes quoth he, taken all after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at their hands that doo think them-ſelues both wiſe and woorſhipfull, yet was there neuer put vnto me ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem as this by any of them, yet drink In C.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. a yéer by them aboue all charges. Fréend quoth the Gentleman, other mens dooing are no preſident vnto me, further then they ſtand with my dutie vnto God, and with the diſcharging of my calling, for he hath bidden vs by his prophet to ſtand vp and enquire after the olde waies, and if they be good: then to goe in them or els not, which béeing ſpoken generally vnto all eſtates: how much more vnto them of my calling, and therfore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that ſuch hard &amp; extreme dealing might ſtand w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dutie of euery priuat perſon, either vnto God or vnto their Cuntry and common welth, or els with their owne aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce-which I vtterly deny, yet could it not ſtand with my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor of any man of my calling. Firſt for the priuat perſon, &amp; to reproue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch extreme dealing ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not with his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:173301:29"/> towards God, of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mandements d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly proo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wherin he ſo ſtraightly comma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eth vnto vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re is, loue &amp; benigniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one towards an other, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the which ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dare not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hée looueth God whom he neuer ſaw, neither th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he hath any faith, now what loue or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie in there in him that letteth vnto his Neighbour a leaſe of hunger, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll miſery &amp; calametie, &amp; ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n, which God forbad to doo vnto the Oxe? The next to wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it ſtandeth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with his dutie to the common welth, the very woord co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> welthe doth ſufficiently ſhowe, for if a man liue in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-welth he muſt haue ſome of the ioyes and fruits therof, or els it is to him no common welth, namely traueling and labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring ſore therin, neither wil he that a man bear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any good w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l toward that common welth wherin the ioyes and ſorowes welth &amp; wee are ſo vnequally deuided and this ſtandeth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the aſſurance of the common welth, which increaſeth by the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, looue &amp; concord, &amp; falleth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> decayeth by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Theſe the two firſt béeing prooue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooue that ſuch extreme taking &amp; exacting ſtandeth all with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſſurance of the very partie himſelf euery priuate mans c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, &amp; this ſéemeth ſtranger and harder to prooue: then the reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>due hath béen, but it is not ſo, namely vnto him that goeth with the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> into the houſe of God &amp; ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for there hee ſhall plainly vnderſtand that all is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot cleerly gotten that is put into the purſſe, for I my ſelfe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e known a number quoth he, that haue raiſed iiij. times double y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues that their anceſters liued welthily &amp; woorſhipful vpon, yea and before their death would fain haue ſolde land if they had had any.</p>
            <p>The cauſe wherof is for that God who is not p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſent nor called to councell in ſuch extreme taking: wil neuer be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent nor giue counſel or aduiſe in the beſtowing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpending of the ſame, either to his honor &amp; glory: or els to their owne benefit, but giueth them ouer to delight in vile and vaine pleaſures, and to be gainfull and ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ficiall vnto the Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of voluptuouſnes and ſenſualitie and flatter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, whoſe fréendſhip endeth when the tap lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th running, and when
<pb facs="tcp:173301:30"/> ſtrange and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uelous vnto you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I will tell you another matter which is an true as this and of mine own experience alſo. I pray you let mée heare Neighbour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uoth <hi>Pierce.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An other tale by the Hoaſt of a yong Gentleman that had morgaged his Land, comming to an other great Officer of the Law to whome hee offered to ſel his land of whome hee had great comfort. Chap. 16.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T fortuned an other time I was in Kent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo at the houſe of an other great and rich Of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficer towards the Laws, where I had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſoiourne certain daies, during which time there c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me thether a yong ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man to offer his Land to ſel, and made an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer therof, vnto this man in my preſence, vnto whome this Woorſhipfull Lawyer ſpake in this maner.</p>
            <p>Wherfore wil you fel your Lands (quoth hée) béeing an ancient poſſeſſion: and a fair liuing? Sir (quoth this yong man) I am fallen into great det comming to my Lands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was wiſe, and haue morgaged any Land for two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound, which except I come within theſe ten dayes: I vtterly loſe any Land.</p>
            <p>You haue brought your ſelf into great extremitie (quoth this Gentleman) how be it, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el your Land: mée think a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> remedie therof, and great pittie if any other way mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtie taken, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lleth away his Land: felleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his beſt and moſte aſſured Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d. Beſides that to ſel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way namely his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cient Patremony and which hée neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is both ſhamefull and ſlaunderous as to haue diſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited &amp; de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his name, houſe &amp; familie, which is an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be thing which the good <hi>Nabothe</hi> the <hi>Iſraelite</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed thervnto the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for when <hi>Achab</hi> demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him his Vineyard for as much as it was woorth, God forbid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that I ſhould ſell thée my Fathers Inheritaunce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éeing yet but a poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iniard: yet did hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d it is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> may read in the old Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament
<pb facs="tcp:173301:30"/> how greatly God himſelf fauored the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntenance and preſeruation of Inheritaunce &amp; poſſeſſion in their <hi>Tribes,</hi> houſes, names and families. For he commaunded by <hi>Moyſes</hi> expreſſely if any man ſolde his Inheritaunce béeing Land or houſe: it ſhould return vnto him again in the yéere of <hi>Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le</hi> which was euery fiftie yéeres. Alſo that Women vnto whom Lands and Inheritaunce were deuolute in default of heires males ſhould not marry into any other <hi>Tril e.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ꝙ hée) I wiſh you to haue a great regarde in departing from your Inheritaunce ſo great a bleſſing of God for it is a great infamie &amp; reproche to be ſaid, an vnthrift an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caier of a houſe &amp; familie whether it were greater or ſmaller.</p>
            <p>Alas ſir (quoth this yong man) I am in greater diſtreſſe, yée knowe theſe Merchaunts of London are hard dealers with whome there is no mercy but for ready pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, wel quoth the Gentleman, I will doo thus much for you, I my ſelf wil lend you an hundreth pound which you ſhal repay by fortie pound a yéer, and that I ſuppoſe you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſely doo ordering your ſelf wiſely, take that quoth hée &amp; off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r it to the Merchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t if happily he may be intreated to giue you a yéer or twain for the reſt vpon reaſonable conſideration, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yong man gaue him harty thanks, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> money was fetched down, counted &amp; deliuered &amp; th'aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce made accordingly, which being doon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yongma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> took his leaue &amp; hartily deſired me (although améer ſtranger vnto him, (yet becauſe I was preſent &amp; a witnes of ſo great curteſie &amp; humanitie) to go with him to London vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Merchants houſe, which I alſo was cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt to doo, and hauing diſpatched the occaſion of my there béeing, and hauing likewiſe taken my leaue: to London wée came and to the Merchants houſe wée went, when wée came before this Merchant the yong Gentleman began to intreat him as feare as hée could and telling him of this good &amp; godly Lawyer and of his great compaſſion, his good councell and perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: deſired him to accept this C.l. in part of paiment, and to giue him a yéere or twaine for payment of the re t. This Merchant hauing heard all the matter: now GOD forbid
<pb facs="tcp:173301:31"/> (quoth he) that euer a Lawyer ſhould heap coales vpon Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants head, or that a Merchant ſhould not be as willing and as ready to doo a godly déed as a Lawyer, hauing receiued at the hands of God the like habilitie therto. And therwithall hauing receiued the C.l. hée took his owne bond for the reſt to be paid by x.l. a yéer, his firſt pay to begin after the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans C.l. ful paid, and deliuered vnto him all his Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and other aſſurances of the Morgage, and making vs great chéere he let vs departe. Now when I would haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my leaue of this yong Gentleman: I could by no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes forbid him to bring mée on my way hitherward, as farre as <hi>Ware</hi> xx. miles on this ſide London, where he paid all my charges for that night, and the next day wée took leaue eache of other and departed either of vs toward his owne. Thus ye ſée how frutful was the good and gracious déed of one man, and how it prouoked the zeale of an other to doo the like.</p>
            <p>A A A A A A A Amen (quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi>) Well quoth our Hoſte, becauſe you doo ſo hardly receiue my proofes: I will bring you more ſtore of them, and ſuch as I am ready to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifye againſt whomſoeuer will deny their trueth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>An other tale of the Hoſte of a woorſhipfull Lawyer that made leaſes to all his tenaunts of the Farmes they held for Li. yeers after a ſtrange ſorte and alſo very wiſely. Chap. 17.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was (quoth hée) in <hi>Buckingham</hi> Shire not very long ſithence, at the houſe of a rich Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer toward the Law whome I could name if néed required, who during the time of my bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, made vnto all his Tenants leaſes of their farmes, wherof I my ſelf am wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, preſent at their Sealing and deliuerye, The leaſes are for li. yéeres from the day of the date therof, the rent reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as followeth. Yéelding and paying vnto the ſaid Leaſſor and his heires yéerly during ſo many of the ſaid li. yéeres as th'inheritaunce ſhall remaine in him or them, not ſolde, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunged, morgaged, forfaited, leaſed in reuertion or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:173301:31"/> eſtraunged v.l. currant money of England, and yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and paying from and immediatly after any ſuch act doon by him or them or any of them v. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. yéerly of like cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rant mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and ſo after the rate of other rents were they greater or ſmaller. Prouided alwaies, that the tenaunt ſhall not ſell, ſet nor let their ſaid Farme or any percel therof, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thout the aſſent and licence of the ſaid Leaſſor or his heires, of which reſeruation I aſked him a reaſon, wherunto hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſwere was this. Sée (quoth hée) how hard a matter it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for yong Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto whom it falleth by the grace and gift of God to be Landlorde and owners, wiſely to order &amp; gou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rn either their poſſeſſions, lands and reuenues or themſelues. I know alſo (quoth hée) that in the wiſdome, prudency an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of ſuch, ſtandeth the happy and proſpere us eſtate of a common welth; and her miſery in the contrary, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my iudgement ought all men generally to wiſh, yea and to endeuour that the greateſt lands and poſſeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions may be in their hands who both can and will order and diſpoſe the ſame to the honor and glory of God and to the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ofit of the common welth, wherin me thinketh ſauing reformation, the to often and to common tranſlation of poſſeſſion is not the leaſt matter nor laſt to be conſidered, as well for the cauſes therof which are euill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as alſo for the effects therof which are wurſe. The cauſes that make men to ſell their patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes and to ſpoyle their inheritance, who knoweth not to be theſe, riot, gaine, whordome, delight in all vngodly pleaſures and paſtime of ſenſualitie, ſhortly the not fearing of God, nor ſeruing him, and the not caring to knowe his wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, nor to liue therafter, theſe are the cauſes. The effects are theſe, firſt the ſpoyle of the land and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> making it barren and bare of all the commodities therof, ſecondly the diſlodging and diſapointing of the honeſt Farmers and good houſe kéepers, for their ſakes that will doo more then they, without any other reſpect, and thoſe are commonly the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly, and from thence ariſeth infini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſutes and controuerſies, maintenaunces, champerties and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>This cauſeth lands often to chaunge their tenaunts and
<pb facs="tcp:173301:32"/> inhabitants, and by that means breacheth and diſſolueth one of the greateſt and ſureſt bonds of looue and fréendſhip that is or euer was, namely, coeducation, conuerſation and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, which hatcheth, nouriſheth and confirmeth looue and fréendſhip, not only betwéen men: but euen betwéen the brute and vnreaſonable beaſts, who hauing béene foſtered long together in one place, will not only looue and defend one an other: but alſo euen the very place wherin they were bred and nouriſhed, and they will very hardly be ſundred or dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen there from. And this is the very law of kinde, which can not effectually woork among neighbours, of whome ſome are dayly or yéerly flitting and giuing place vnto new, namely ſuch as will bid more the which commonly are the wurſer ſorte as hath béen already alleaged. Theſe are two effects.</p>
            <p>The third is the ſinceritie of Iuſtice and alſo of dicipline both which it greatly hazardeth, namely for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buyers and ſellers are Corelatiues, and that the one cannot be without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and for that alſo the cauſes of ſelling &amp; ſpoyling of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonies are ſuch as I haue already declared. Theſe things are right perillous in a common welth, and yet doo almoſte neceſſarily followe the too often and common tranſlation of poſſeſſion and inheritaunce, namely where it is by peny pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, againſt the which neuertheleſſe it is meruelous hard to foreſée and to prouide, I meane for heires and inheritours of Lordſhips, Lands and poſſeſſions to continue in the ſame, béeing things that ſo many deſire to haue, yea oftentimes ſuch as haue in their hands the bridle of libertie, or reſtraint of good and euill, and of the liues and manners of men, for what is there in all this earth ſo much deſired as houſes, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Lordſhips and poſſeſſions, and to commaund ouer peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? What els is the end of all ſo many and great trauels, watch, ſtudie ſo many and ſo great hazards by Sea and land, ſo many ſhifts, ſleights, deceits and oppreſſions, of all which this world hath béen, is &amp; euer wil be full, againſt all which who ſo will holde a thing of ſo great value: he muſt be well prouided and of great defence, and hath néed to haue in him ſelf the ſtrength, wiſdome, councell and iudgement of many,
<pb facs="tcp:173301:32"/> and ſo much the rather by how much his poſſeſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that for two cauſes. Firſt for that in his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rour of life fall and miſgouernment: lyeth the fall, ruin and decay of a number, what of his owne blood, what of his tenaunts, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full freends and ſeruants. Secondly for that his eſtate is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto many enimies, of whom the greateſt and moſte dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous is the flatterer the olde enemie of all mankinde, as the ſtory of our Father <hi>Adam</hi> and mother <hi>Eue</hi> and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent dooth well declare. This mooued <hi>Iuno</hi> as <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id</hi> fableth to commit <hi>Io</hi> her Cow vnto <hi>Argus</hi> to kéep, which <hi>Argus</hi> had an hundred eyes in his head, and therfore much adooe had <hi>Mercury</hi> to deceiue him withall his ſwéet ſongs and Muſick, for when he had brought on of his eyes a ſleep, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea diuers of them, yet waked diuers other and ſtood vpon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir ward, and whether his face or his back were towards <hi>Io</hi> yet he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way beheld her.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>¶ A reaſon why Coppyholdes, Cuſtomes and Corporations, were firſt ordained, and how that Pride and Flattery are the cheef cauſes that many a yong Gentleman commeth to ſell his Lands. Chap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd ſurely in mine oppinion this mooued the wiſe &amp; honorable fathers &amp; Maieſtrates of old time to incorporat ſo great liuings &amp; poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; alſo to erect &amp; eſtabliſh in Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dſhips ſo many coppy holds and cuſtummar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tenures as the moſte ſoueraigne remedy againſt pride and ſurcuydrie, which commonly accompanieth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> priuate, ſinguler &amp; ſole proprietie in land, poſſeſſion, office or any other thing whatſoeuer, &amp; alſo a way and meane to furni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon welth with many both able to deſerue well and to doo good alſo glad and willing therto, vnto the which p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the only let and impediment: or els of all othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt as he vpon whom flattery attendeth, yea and in ſuch ſorte that he leadeth him by the noſe vp and down the houſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:173301:33"/> him to beléeue of himſelf any thing, cauſing him alſo to delight no while in any one thing, whether it be apparell or the faſhion therof, place, perſon, dyet, fréend, ſeruant, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt or other thing what ſoeuer, and this as dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth, is the high and ready way to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Vſurers houſe and from thence to the Extorcioner, who dwelleth hard by, of which twaine by that time he hath taken foorth his leſſon kindely: I dare be his ſuretie hée wil not be haſty to doo good to any good body, neither if he would ſhall he haue wherwith all, for either ſhall he haue no lands left him at all: or if he haue any, he ſhall be glad to let them déerer then that any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man ſhall doo good thereon, ſo that in concluſion, both th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Landlord and the tenaunt ſhalbe miſerable.</p>
            <p>The cauſe héerof is Pride moſte and chéeftly, as I haue ſaid, and oftentimes youth, good nature, or peraduenture exceſſe of Pleaſure and Senſuall delights, where through yong Gentlemen are often ſnared through euill company, béeing ouertaken ſometime by giuing their woord, ſometime through a bribe of a little preſent mony, ſometime by one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, ſometime by an other, wherin men are ſoone pampred, namely ſuch as are of ſmall experience and iudgement, and knowe not the falſe lures of the wicked and vngodly, aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt all which theſe Corporations and cuſtomes are of great force and a great defence, for in both theſe caſes: hardly can they be aſſaulted, much leſſe inuaded by any of the enemies aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Firſt for that a corporation is neuer vnder age, as for example, Maior and Comminaltie, Deane, and Chapter, Wardens and Fellowes and ſuch like, whoſe ſucceſſion is by election, their proprietie is ioynt and in common, neither can one doo any thing without the reſt, and therfore to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any one of them vaine, and to flatter them all very hard namely mens Natures, Wit, Iudgements and Affections béeing diuers, and euery man willing to maintaine and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his owne opinion or his fréends. Pride atteinteth them not, for who is proud, or at the leaſt ſo proud of any thing, wherin a number hath to commaund as much as he, and
<pb facs="tcp:173301:33"/> without whom he can doo nothing, then béeing armed againſt Pride the Father of neceſſitie and néed: they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etter frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to afforde their good woord or déed, and therfore in vaine were it to bribe them.</p>
            <p>But admit that any of them would be bribed, it were alſo in vaine and would procure the euill will of all the reſt with out bribing them all which were heauy and hard to doo.</p>
            <p>So that in any competicion made vnto ſuch perſons againſt any olde Fréend, Tenaunt, Officer or ſeruant: it is very hard to preuaile except it be through his owne great miſbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour. And where it is betwéen méere Sraung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs one of them againſt an other, there the beſt and moſte woorthy is ſure to ſpéed, for certainly and infallible there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othing in all this world ſo amiable, ſo beloued and fauoured as honeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vertue and godlines are. Where priuate flatterie or briberie ſtand not in their light, as in the caſe of priuate Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and proprietaries: I haue alleadged that it both may and often dooth. And thus much of the Corporations &amp; of their effects. Now to ſpeake of the cuſtomes of Manours the very ſame or like in effect may be ſaid, for the Inheritour of cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Land although hée be ſeaſed therof to him and to his heires yet can hée not ſel it without licence of the Lord and that ſolemnly graunted by his Steward in open Court and there entred, nay hée cannot ſet or let the ſame or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>therwiſe impaire the wood or other commodities therof without lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>So great an entreſſe and commaundement hath the Lord therin and yet not to the hinderaunce or preiudice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce but <hi>e contra,</hi> namely that the ſelling, ſetting or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gouernment of ſuch a royall poſſeſſion as land <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: ſhould ſtand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudgement &amp; diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diuers, &amp; thoſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ripeſt &amp; beſt aduiſed, and not to be ſolde, waſted or ſpoyled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intemperaunce of one fooliſh or vngodly man or woman ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther formed or neceſſitie or otherwiſe for flatery or other fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or fooliſh affection whatſoeuer, wherin the Lord and his ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Stuard and the homagers of the Court are Iudges.</p>
            <p>In all which caſe it may euidently appéer how great a care
<pb facs="tcp:173301:34"/> thoſe honourable and reuerend Forefathers had to enact and eſtabliſh the great poſſeſſions in the hands of ſuch as were not like to miſregarde ſo great and high a bleſſing of GOD, the effects and fruites wherof haue béen many and great as from time to time proof hath verified and yet dooth, for it hath alwaies béen accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; yet is a right happy thing to be tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or Farmer to a Corporation or enioy any commoditie vnder them. For woorſhipful &amp; honorable haue alwaies béen their dealing in ordering and gouernment of their Lands, liuings, and poſſeſſions. and of their Tenaunts and Farmers of the ſame. But chéefly and abooue all others to be Tenaunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prince, who indéed is a Corporation, for from the Prince, there can paſſe nothing but by writing vnder ſeale, neither dooth or can w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the conſent of diuers of the moſte honorable and beſt aduiſed. Theſe (quoth hée) are the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the reaſons that haue mooued mée to make theſe lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and therin theſe reſeruations which vnto you doo ſéeme ſo very ſtrange. For I ſuppoſe this to be a ſtrong meane to vnite the Landlord and his tenaunt togither, and to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terballaunce the one of them againſt the other in fourme of a corporation, or els as néer vnto the Nature therof as I could deuiſe. For by this meanes, if my heires or any of them chaunce at any time héerafter to proue vnthrifty: his vnthrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines ſhall not be ſo gainfull vnto any man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in hope to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his lands would therfore ſtrengthen his hands therin and by theſe means I haue left them moe Frends and fewer Flatterers. For hée that ſhal buy his lands without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Farmer: hée ſhall for the time make as good a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe as dooth hée that purchaſeth of a Woman her Huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds lands while hée is yet aliue, or he that goeth to the Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and buying there a Capon for two ſhillings putteth him into his bag, and when he commeth home he findeth there nothing but a Capons leg, for in this caſe of mine: the buyer buyeth leſſe then the Seller ſelleth by xix. partes, which me think ſhould kéep them from argument vpon the price whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt either of them would fain make the beſt bargain for him ſelf, as the maner of all chapmen is. And for which reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:173301:34"/> 
               <hi>Ieſus Sirach</hi> ſaith of them, that ſinne ſticketh betwéen the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the ſeller as faſt as dooth a nail ſtick betwéen two ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es in a wall.</p>
            <p>This way haue I brought to be ſtronger and better aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then any entaile generall or ſpeciall both whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h priuate couetiſe hath found a way to deſtroy to the diſheriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a good kinred and to the great decay of vertue and godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and héerin (quoth hée) I haue doon my heirs n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wrong, for vpon this rent I haue liued conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and doo, &amp; if they prooue honeſt and vertuous: ſo may they doo, and then I haue left them inough. and if they prooue otherwiſe: then hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I left to much and yet to little to ſerue them alſo.</p>
            <p>Moreouer (quoth hée) I haue héerby prouided againſt the malice of ſuch tenaunts as abuſe the liberalitie of good Land lords fetting and letting ouer vnto the third and fourth hand racking and enhaunſing the things vnto exceſſiue and vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable rents, and ſuch as the Landlord him ſelf would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue doon for pure ſhame and pittie, which neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe béeing raiſed to his hand by others: is a perillous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident vnto him at his return vnto the poſſeſſion therof.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard (quoth our Hoſte) what a godly and Fatherly care this good and vertuous Maieſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e had to preferre the honour and glory of God and alſo the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommon welth of his Cuntry and People, whereby it may appéere how hartely to be deſired is the purchaſe of ſuch P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſonnes whoſe riches is the Treaſury and Storehouſe of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, aſwell for the ſuſtenaunce of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning worldly and bodily prouiſion of tranſitorie things: as alſo for the furtherance and increaſe of Vertue, godlines and Pietie, Looue and Concord.</p>
            <p>Ho (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) lay a ſtraw there for Gods ſak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, marry Sir héer is ſtuffe indéed (quoth he) heer hath béen a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe indéed, and euen as true as all the reſt, with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted their talke and ſpake vnto him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>The Author interrupteth Pierce maintaining Simons Aſſertion ſhewing that of late in his ſight he knew a Lawyer gaue x.li.
<pb facs="tcp:173301:35"/> to the building of a Bridge. Chap. 19.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ather <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth I) theſe matters are not ſo ſtrange nor ſo incredible as you wéene, for proof wherof I will (if it pleaſe you to giue me leaue) to reherſe a thing which I my ſelf did ſe and that no longer a go then Eaſter Tearme laſt. It fortuned that I went into a Lawyers Chamber in Sergeants Inne with a Fréend of mine who was Plaintiff in a repleuin in Bedford ſhire, and being come into his Law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yers Chamber and hauing ſtaied there a while about our bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſines: there came in an ancient Gentleman of the Cuntry, whome I know very wel by ſight and haue doon long, whom when the Maiſter had eſpied comming vp euen at the top of the ſtaires, hée ſpake to him as followeth. I know wherfore you come, go down again to my man and bid him come vp to mée, which the Gentleman bid, his ſeruant béeing come: he took foorth of his Cubbord (which was vnder the ſquare ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble that ſtood before him) a bagge wherin was ten pound and deliuering it vnto his man bad him go down and pay it vnto the Gentleman, and if any of the golde lack waight chaunge it for him. The ſeruant went downe and did accordingly, I thought verily it had béen the rent of ſome houſe or land that he had holden of him. But euen while I was in this thought: the Gentleman comming vp again gaue him humble &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thanks and that in the name and behalfe of a whole Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie yea of diuers Shires. Wherupon I taking occaſion to enquire farther of the matter: vnderſtood that he gaue that ten pound fréely towards the erecting &amp; building of a bridge, and that ſuch charitable déeds as this are no new things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. I ſooner wil beléeue this (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) hauing of a man learned in the Lawes and whom Vertue and Learning haue prefferred, then of the others that Fiſhen for Offices with the golden hook and neuer wiſt what Learning ment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:35"/>
            <head>Simons returne to his matter again declareth of an other rich Of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficer in the Law who had two Farmers, one rich and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poore and how he delt with them. Chap. 20.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith that our Hoſte took holde again, ſaying y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hée had yet one other matter to tell and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he would conclude. I was an other time (quoth hée) at the houſe of an other rich Officer towards the Law, who d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elleth in Kent alſo and is a man of great w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lth, and one time of my béeing at his houſe as (I thank hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) I haue béen very many times. There were two of his Tenaunts come to take new leaſes of their Farmes the land<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> béeing of equall rent &amp; value, but yet the Farmers not equal in welth: the one hauing béen bleſſed (as it ſhould ſeem) abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the other for the one of them was very welthie and vpheld h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in very good repaire &amp; offered the Lord at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt woord forty pound for a fine for one and twenty yéers The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was poore and yet his tenament in decay, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther was hée able to giue fiue pounds for a fine, wherof the Landlord hauing challenged him and warning him to look to it theraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: willed the other to lay down his forty pounds, which hée did without delay. The Gentleman when hée had coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it: put it into a bagge and fréely gaue it vnto the poor man with theſe woords (one of you beare an others burd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the other was ſo farr from béeing ill content that hée humbly praiſed God, and gaue the Gentleman right hartie thanks therfore: and ſo he ſent them away bothe very well contented. Since which time I héer of the poore man that hée is growen to great welth and of ſuch benigniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitie as are not many Owners or Landlords dwelling néer him. Thus (quoth our Hoſte) I haue confirmed my firſt Aſſertion and haue ſufficiently auoyded your reaſons and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples alleadged in diſproof of the ſame, and theſe haue I doon by Example and demonſtrations dothe moe in number then yours are: and alſo more euident, apt and prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173301:36"/> purpoſe. That is not ſo Neighbour (quoth <hi>pierce</hi>) for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that your Examples were all or any of them true, which for the moſte parte I will not graunt, yet are they per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticuler and cannot make any generall Concluſion, beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you tender mée an iſſue vpon two affirmatiues which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the grounds of law as I haue learned by mine owne experience déerly bought. For I haue alleadged againſt you the penerall Corruption of liues and manners béeing the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect of libertie vnto exceſſe and diſſolution which I alſo haue alleadged and prooued to be an effect of priuate deſire to pouch to purchaſe and to wax rich, from al which cauſes and effects conuertly my Argument is neceſſary and infallible and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore béeing alleadged affirmatiuely it demaundeth a direct &amp; generall trauerſe to the effects, which effects béeing not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued: the cauſes therof cannot be denied, againſt all which matters you haue anſwered in the affirmatiue alſo, allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the examples of ſome good men, which whether they be true or not, I doo not greatly force without a generall denyal of that which I haue alleadged, although that for euery ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample alleadged you had brought fiftéen, and ſo is my firſt Aſſertion maintained and ſtandeth faſt, and yours vtterly diſprooued.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>The Concluſion of the Conference, and the preparation to the Queſtions beeing the ſecond Book. Chap. 21.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y this time it was waxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen dark night and our Hoaſt ſpeaking vnto <hi>Pierce</hi> ſaid vnto him Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth hée) wée haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned ſo very long to and fro that the night is ſtolen vpon vs, and the purpoſe of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming hither vtterly forgoten through our ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt diſputation in theſe matters.</p>
            <p>Truely Neighbour (ꝙ <hi>Pierce</hi>) I cannot think this time ill ſpent, I would I had neuer ſpent time wurſſe if it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:173301:36"/> God, and therfore quoth he, if it pleaſe you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o lend mée this v.l. I will be gon home, for I knowe the way at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte) your v.l. is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ye ſhall haue it with you but not to nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for hence ſhal ye not departe before to morowe God willing, and name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for this ſtrangers ſake, whome I wil deſire yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany for this night, for in his Cuntry I haue re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eiued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny folde humanitie, as partly ye haue heard, and therfore I gladly would doo him ſome héere to my power, and therfore this night or a conuenient part therof wée will in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euour our ſelues to ſpend together in honeſt mirth and exerciſes. And therwithall I ſpake, and geuing our Hoſte harty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hanks: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <hi>Pierce</hi> that it might ſo be. Who at my reque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t did ſoone condiſcend, and was very wel contented therwith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll.</p>
            <p>Then quoth I, ſéeing that we haue ſo wel ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the fore part of the night wherin I my ſelf haue doon nothing but har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened: let vs agrée vpon ſome meane to paſſe the time with all after ſupper vntil bed time, no wurſſe then we haue doon the time before.</p>
            <p>Now verily Gentleman (quoth our Hoſte) and that is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well ſpoken, I be ſhrewe him that diſagreeeth therunto, if it be my ſelf. Amen quoth <hi>Pierce Plowman</hi> if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e I. Very well then quoth I, this is my order if it may pleaſe you. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Supper euery man ſhall put his queſtion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el his tale in order, &amp; by courſe wherunto eche of the others ſhall ſpeak to wit vnto the queſtion ſhall giue an anſwere of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſſolution of the ſaying and vnto the tale ſhall ſhew their good or il like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hée that telleth the beſt and wiſeſt tale to wit of high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt and beſt ſentence and putteth the ſharpeſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſeſt queſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion moſte tending to vertue and edifying of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earers or giues the wiſeſt and beſt ſolution: hée ſhall haue his breakfaſt héer to morrow at the charges of the other twain. Content withall my hart quoth our Hoſte. Content qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman. But to whoſe Iudgement ſhal we ſtand héerin ꝙ hée? Truely ꝙ I, euen to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oome of our Hoſteſſe fit pleaſe her to take it vpon her, wherupon ſhée béeing calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lingly vndertook it, ſo was the matter fully agrée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and on
<pb facs="tcp:173301:37"/> hands giuen there vpon. And then was the fable couered for ſupper &amp; (our Hoſte hauing him ſell firſt giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thanks to God) to ſupper wée went where wée fared right wel &amp; were mery, and when wée had ſupped: the Cloth béeing remooued, and thanks likewiſe giuen. After wée had ſitten ſtil and repoſed our ſelues a little while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my ſelf began as followeth.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Book.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <head>The Second Book, declaring the Queſtions and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers between the Author, the Hoſte, and Pierce Plowman.</head>
            <p n="1">1 THe firſt Queſtion put by me, whether it be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to vertue and godlynes to giue or to lend, or to pay that a man oweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pierce Plowman</hi> anſwered, that of thoſe thrée to giue was the beſt, to lend was the next, &amp; as for paying that which a man oweth: he held it a duty, &amp; in dooing of duty there ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no Godlynes, neither lieth there any thank therin, &amp; that (he ſaid) appéereth by <hi>Chriſte</hi> his owne woords who ſayeth, that when wée haue doon that which was our duty: wée are vnprofitable ſeruants, neither hath paying, of debts any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe teſtimony of Godlynes or vertue, in the Scriptures of God, or by common experience among men, wheras giuing hath a name of vertue, namely of liberallitie wherof the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh thus. He hath diſperſed and giuen vnto the poore, and his righteouſnes remaineth for euer. Again oof lending he ſaith. The righteous is mercifull and lendeth, and will guide his woords with diſcreſion. To be ſhort, liberalitie (which extendeth both vnto giuing and alſo lending) is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of God, who both giueth and lendeth vnto vs his dayly gifts and bleſſings, but borowe he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not neither pay his debt. And ſo ſhortly paying of debt in his opinion no vertue ne pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertie of Godlines, for that it is a thing which God him ſelf cannot doo, and ſo the firſt twaine, vertues and the third no vertue, but a duty.</p>
            <p>OVr Hoſte maintained the contrary, &amp; that to pay a mans debt is the moſte excellent qualitie &amp; vertue of the thrée,
<pb facs="tcp:173301:37"/> and moſte peculier and proper vnto the children o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, and that the other twaine are no vertues, neither d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſerue that name, ſaue ſo far foorth as they are included within this, and for proofe therof thus he reaſoneth. Whatſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s or may be cauſe of euill: that ſame thing may it ſelf be ſaid to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. What ſoeuer act corrupteth or diſhoneſteth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dooer or the ſufferer therof, or els bothe: that act is or may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> euil, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, whatſoeuer act dooth not neither cann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t corrupt or diſhoneſt the dooer nor the ſufferer therof nor an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon; that act ſaith he neither is euill, neither by any meanes can be made or called euil. Lending ſaith he oft tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and diſhoneſteth the dooer therof, namely for Vſurye, ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling the déerer for day giuen, both theſe are lendin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in their kindes, and yet not any properties of Godlines no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vertue.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeak of the beſt lending and that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imply w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any of the regards aforeſaid, yet meaneth the lender to haue his things again, and therfore what godlyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s is there ſaith <hi>Chriſte</hi> if you bid them to dinner y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can bid yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againe, what great godlynes haue you ſhewed therin, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o much of lending. Gifts are giuen oft-times to corrupt and ſo peruert Iuſtice, and therby both the dooer and ſufferer diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oneſted. Gifts are giuen by the couetous in hope to receiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greater. Gifts are giuen by flatterers and Clawbacks, nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and exceſſiue feaſts and banquets vnto P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inces and great eſtates, to the end vnder their authoritie to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide vpon the poore and godly people, and to deuoure and ſpoyle the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of all others of the common and meaner ſorie, to the great oppreſſion of vertue and godlynes, and to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of al wickednes and vngodlynes. Gifts are g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of frendſhipp when nothing is ſo little m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, and ſo wickednes vtterly concluded therby: In giuing is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vaine glory, and theſe two are the fathers a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d mother of flattery. For where <hi>Thraſo</hi> is <hi>Gnatho</hi> wil be alſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, giuing vnto one fréend and not vnto the reſt, if a man ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> procureth their hatred and enuye againſt both the giuer and the receiuer. Shortly it ſtandeth togither to be a large giuer: and yet a moſte wicked and vngodly perſon, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erof are
<pb facs="tcp:173301:38"/> great examples namely of <hi>Cateline,</hi> of whom <hi>Saluſt</hi> writeth that he was prodigall of his owne, &amp; deſirous of other mens. And of <hi>Silla</hi> that cruell Tirant hée reporteth this, he would giue no man more frankly, lend he would alſo very liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but what ſoeuer he could borowe: he would neuer pay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Now vnto the third part, to wit paying a mans debt, and which (ſaith he) I call the moſte high and ſoueraign ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the moſte proper vnto Godlines, and that for theſe cauſes. Firſt it neither corrupteth nor diſh neſteth the dooer nor the ſufferer therof, for I am ſure al men wil confeſſe that a man may honeſtly pay that which he oweth, and he vnto whom he ought it, may honeſſly craue the ſame.</p>
            <p>Paying of def corrupteth no Iuſtice neither I ſuppoſe can be prooued euer to haue doon in paying of bet there is no oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vaine glory, for it is not the déed of a proud minde, whoſe propertie is not to acknowledg any good turn for that might charge him with duty of acquitall wheron the proud and vngodly differ chéefly from vertuous and godly, for the proud may not ſéeme to haue néeded any mans good turn nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue vſed their help, both which things in paying their det they ſhould implicatiuely confeſſe to haue doon, and therfore are they aſhamed to repay what ſo they can borrow for the Concluſion aforeſaid. And that ſtandeth wel with the ſaying of Ieſus of <hi>Sirack</hi> who ſaith that what ſo the vngodly can borrowe: hée accounteth it as if hée had found it, wherof the reaſon is this, although pure néed and neceſſitie conſtrain them oft to vſe this woord (lend) yet they vſe him for a cloke of diſſimulation as the effect ſheweth, for this is euident that there are but foure waies of attainment or getting of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer thing, for it is either giuen vs, lent vs, or els wée take it perforce, or els wée found it.</p>
            <p>So that whatſoeuer is lent vnto ſuch people either it is giuen or lent, or taken by force or els found.</p>
            <p>Giuen you wil ſay it is not, nor ſo ment by you, and you ſhall finde the ſame by him that took it at your hands, for hée will neuer giue you thanks therfore, neither ſée you but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his hart.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:38"/>
            <p>Borowed it was not vpon his behalf, and conſeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ently not vpon yours, howſoeuer you ment in departing the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>with for except there be a borower: there can be no lender, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they are corelatiue and none can be without other, no mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then there can be a Father without a Childe, then if the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e did not borrowe: the other did not lend, hée borrowed not, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r you ſhall finde that with his good will hée neuer ment to pay it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your lent it not.</p>
            <p>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> took not from you perforce for your ſelf deliuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d it, ſo thou if you neither gaue it, lent it, neither left by f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rce, then there remaineth but a fourth, which is that you loſt it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hee hath found it, according to the ſaying of <hi>Ieſus</hi> of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rack,</hi> for what ſoeuer a man findeth hee took it from n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man neither is he bound to thank any man therfore, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this is the manner of the vngodly: the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>areth witneſſe where hée ſaith <hi>The vngodly boroweth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayeth not again, but the righteous is mercifull and liberall,</hi> Thus it appéereth (quoth our Hoſte) that who ſo truely paieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t hée can not therin be called an euil perſon or be ſaid to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſted neither him ſelf or any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odie, and therin farre excelleth this quallitie both the other.</p>
            <p>¶ But now it reſteth mée to prooue (quoth hée) th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t this word (to pay a mans det) dooth include both the reſt ſo farre ſaith as they may or can be called vertues or proper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies of godlines which I wil prooue in this order.</p>
            <p>¶ Firſt ſay, that whatſoeuer wée haue héer in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orld: wée haue it at the bountifull &amp; mercifull hands of our God as lent and which hée may at his pleaſure take from vs, as alſo wée dayly ſee him doo. Then if wée haue nothing but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at we haue receiued: (as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith) wée muſt needs c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfeſſe wée are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tted vnto him therfore. How then can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e pay vnto him our det for hée receiueth no money we canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> feaſt him, for hée neither eateth Buls fleſh nor drinketh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blood of Goates. It reſteth then that wée giue vnto them that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Bayliffes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ereiuers for that intent a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and vnto them in whoſe perſoune<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hée hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d him ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to wit unto his poore and godly Saints a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts
<pb facs="tcp:173301:39"/> that are héer vpon the Earth among vs, vnto whome whatſoeuer wée giue hée hath promiſed to accept it, as giuen vnto him as a payment of ſo much det, a teſtimony not of our merit: but of our woorking faith in his grace and mercy, and in this only ſence and meaning, giuing and lending are vertues and proper vnto the Children of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THe next Queſtion put by our Hoſte, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whether is the harder matter to make a Lord or a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pierce</hi> anſwered, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in all common reaſon &amp; alſo by experience the harder thing: the harder is the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing therof, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hée) is a greater degrée then a Gentleman, and therfore har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be made then a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Anſwered that I thought and knew the contrary by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, For I knew (quoth I) where a Churle by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> purchaſe of Mannour is become Lord of a number better men then himſelf, and ſo is hée a Lord and yet no Gentle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. THe next Queſtion of <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman was why p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men are not called to office of eſtate and gouernment in common welths but euermore the rich and welthy.</p>
            <p>OVr Hoſte anſwered, becauſe quoth hée, the poore would to be rich and ſo are not content with their preſent eſtate, but to deſire alteration and chaunge and all ſuch perſones are more méet to be commaunded then to commaund in a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth. But of the rich and welthie it is clean otherwiſe, for they are already that which the poore haue deſire to be, and therfore content, and conſequently Fréends and furtherers of peace and vnitie which is neuer nor neuer wil be where they haue authoritie in their hands that are not content with their owne preſent ſtate, and ſo great hazard of the common peace lieth therin.</p>
            <p n="4">4 THe next Queſtion by mé<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is the reaſon that the Sonnes and Children of great purchaſers, namely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; and Merchants, are common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſuch hee ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and
<pb facs="tcp:173301:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173301:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173301:40"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>meleſſe vnthrifts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PIerce</hi> anſwerered that hée knew no reaſon therin but hée thought it a very ſecret Iudgement of God vpon the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents that haue eaten foure Grapes and ſet their Childr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>edge.</p>
            <p>OVr Hoſte ſaid it argued great equitie and conſience in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir Children in that they ment to buy wit, and to pay as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éer therfore as their fathers and fréends had ſold theirs.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The next Queſtion by our Hoſte, what was firſt the reaſon of giuing and wearing of mourning gownes and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for ſuch as are deceaſed.</p>
            <p>PIerce anſwered hée thought it was in fauour of our i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie and weaknes, and for that reaſon: are not ſo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one and ready to wéep ſo ſore, namely rich widowes who ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>not wéep ſo redily as a dog can make water, and therfore it was thought expedient that ſuch mourning were, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld not mourne for other buſines: they might be al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d vnto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſoone honeſt and coulorable meanes to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urn by atturney, as wée ſée y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in matters of law he that for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther neceſſary buſines cannot attend vpon his cauſes: is receiued by his Attourney, and of theſe great heires, executor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and rich widowes that are otherwiſe neceſſarily occupied and haue no leiſure to wéep: it was thought in like maner. Alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thought profitable for the parties themſelues for that it is an honeſt mean of publicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſwel of the widowh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d as alſo of her great heuines, therfore wherby the more Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelers may reſort vnto her, for in ſtrange places a wido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is known from other by her wéeping and ſorow.</p>
            <p n="6">6 THe next Queſtion by <hi>pierce</hi> what differeth a cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tous perſon from a Niggard. ¶ Our Hoſte anſwered a ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gard is affraid to want him ſelf, and therfore huſbandeth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and oft liueth beſides his owne. But the couet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us is curſſe affraid leaſt others ſhould not want and therfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth and engroſſeth all to defraude the hungrie ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the poore want bread.</p>
            <p n="7">7 THe next Queſtion by mée why ſuch fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as delight in rich and coſtly apparell, and alſo in deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t and dainty neats
<pb facs="tcp:173301:41"/> and drinks, doo not eat and drink in the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtréets as they doo weare their apparell. ¶ <hi>Pierce</hi> anſwered, becauſe that for their delicate fare: no body would honor or reuerence the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they gaue them part with them, which becauſe they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not to doo: therfore they holde it beſt to eat it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in doores and in ſecret, but in their braue apparell there lieth ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor at the leaſt as they ſuppoſe, becauſe they ſée many y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> méet them ſtrike their ſailes therat although as great and the like reaſon in the one as in the other.</p>
            <p n="8">8. THe next Queſtion by our Hoſte why the beſt and dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt meats and drinks and ſuch as bréed and make the moſts and beſt nuriſhment in the body, doo not alſo bréed the beſt ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner but rather the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Anſwered, becauſe that commonly folke take to much of them, and haue ſo great felicitie therin, the rather that the miniſters of voluptuouſnes and ſenſualitie may thriue, but the chéefeſt and beſt reaſon ſéemeth to be this that me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may knowe that Godlines and vertue are not tied vnto meat and drink, neither doo conſiſt therin, as <hi>Chriſte</hi> hath ſaid. The kingdome of heauen is neither meat nor drink, and to moue vs therfore to eat and drink to liue, and not to liue to eat and drink.</p>
            <p n="9">9. THe next Queſtion by me, what poſſeſſion is the beſt and ſureſt, and leaſt ſubiect vnto rauin and violence.</p>
            <p>OVr Hoſte anſwered the beſt things and the wurſt for ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which is the beſt poſſeſſion, a man may carry farre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough without béeing robbed therof, and or that either man or woman offer to take it from him, and as it is of the beſt: ſo is it of the wurſt, for once (quoth hée) I loſt a Gloue which was taken vp and brought after me.</p>
            <p n="10">10 THe next Queſtion by our Hoſte, whether beautie and honeſtie may dwell togither in one houſe, and be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunts both vnto one Landlord or not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PIerce</hi> ſaid, he knew no cauſe to the contrary, except the Landlord (quoth he) to be a Purchaſer of Land, or a great builder or both, then Beautie muſt haue a Licence of the
<pb facs="tcp:173301:41"/> Iuſtice to kéep a Seller or a bowling alley or an in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdinary table or els all thrée, and then honeſtie muſt take a houſe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of.</p>
            <p n="11">11. THe next Queſtion by <hi>Pierce,</hi> what is the reaſon that ſome Women doo ſo curſe and lay forth their haires.</p>
            <p>THe anſwere by our Hoſte, for that to be berdl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe is in a man monſtrous, and to be bauld headed in a woman as in a trée neuer to haue leaues, or ground graſſe, and therfore leaſt for want of ſhewing their haires they might peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be ſuſpected to be monſters: they make themſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ues very moſters in déed.</p>
            <q>Dum vitant ſtulti vicua in contrarium currum.</q>
            <p n="12">12. THe next Queſtion by our Hoſte, what is the end and purpoſe of ſo ſtately and ſumptuous buildin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſo many Chimneyes therin now a dayes.</p>
            <p>THe anſwere by <hi>Pierce</hi> phiſick and naturall, that againſt all ſickneſſes, namely <hi>Ethicks</hi> and <hi>ptiſicks,</hi> all things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bting the ſences are holſome, and alſo al things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rouoking &amp; cauſing appetite. Theſe delight the ſences, namel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the eyes, theſe ſharpen the appetite, for they argue hunger and ſcarſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie within, neither is the ſmell of meat and drink h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtfull to weak ſtomacks, the Kitchin and the Buttrye béeing not ſo apparant, and euen at the firſt entry as in the olde buildings but rather farre of, and hard to finde, and with ſome labour and exerciſe except to him that knoweth which way they are His reaſon <hi>oeconomicall</hi> politik, that it is a good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the haunt of Beggers, for there is no begge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that hath either experience or wit that will goe thether for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m almes, and ſo mony and charges ſaued therby.</p>
            <p n="13">13. THe next Queſtion by me, wherin differed flatterers from Crowes and Rauens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PIerce</hi> anſwered, they differ in this, that Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens will pick out a mans eyes when hée is de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d but flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers wil eat him while hée is yet aliue.</p>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:42"/>
            <p>this place, there fell a brabble betwéen two rich men concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning trepaſſes by woords &amp; ſpéeches, wherupon one of them ſued the other &amp; had demanded by action M. l' damages. I can not tell how, at length they were both content to put the rout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter vnto two men of worſhip their neighbours, and became bound in great ſinnes either to other to ſtand to their awards &amp; order therin. The plaintif for their better inſtructed deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnto tharbitrators a copy of his declaration &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole iſſue, wherin the party Defendant to ſome of the matter had pleaded not giltie: &amp; other ſome had iuſtified, wherupon th'ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrators hauing duely conſidered, and heard the in allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rther pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f of both their matters, ordered as fole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that the partie defendant béeing guiltie of diuers miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behauiours by the Plaintife againſt him alleadged: ſhould therfore pay two hundred fiftie pound vnto the common tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of fiue Pariſhes next adioining, to be there imploied and beſtowed at the diſcretion of the moſte honeſt and beſt at the ſaid Pariſhes and vnto the partie plaintif for all his coſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this awarde béeing ſhewed and read vnto the parties they were both highly diſpleaſed therat.</p>
            <p>The plaintif for that the Arbitrators had giuen that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Strangers (ſaith hée) which ſhould haue béen his and ſo haue excéeded the limits of their authoritie and the tenour of his ſubmiſſion. The defendant thought him gréeued with the greatnes of the ſum and ſo both the parties highly diſpleaſed.</p>
            <p>The Arbitrators maintained their awarde and order to be both iuſt and reaſonable. Firſt for the Defendaunt, they ſaid they were of duety bond to puniſh him vpon good &amp; due proofs made by his Aduerſarie of his the vngodly behauiour, where neuertheleſſe they had qualified his puniſhment and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde by his Aduerſary. As touching the plaintif and the ſum which hée demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the name and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earin of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends: their anſwere was that they ment it ſuch to wit an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends and that not only vnto one of them but to them both for they hoped that the Defendaunt by that time hée hath pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the two hundred &amp; fiftie pounds wil be better héerafter as concerning the like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce and ſo hée hath his amends, but
<pb facs="tcp:173301:42"/> what or how you would haue béen amended by the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceit of ſo much money paid vnto you: if it might haue appéer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d vnto vs: wee verily would haue adiudged it vnto you, but that could wée neuer perceiue nor be perſwaded to beleeue, for w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neuer heard that honor, vertue, godlynes and the exiſtimation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are or euer were valued or valuable by money <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aking, but rather in departing there from, for as the laſt doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſhew a noble, gentle and a godly hart and mynde: ſo dooth the firſt argue the moſt vile abiect and baſeſt minded perſon that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer can be &amp; one in whome is vtterly miſpriſon of all vertue as wel witneſſeth S. <hi>Peter</hi> vnto <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erfore (ſaid they) we thought that in this diſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we mean to be your act: you haue vnto the world ſufficiently di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>prooued whatſoeuer euil your Aduerſary hath purpoſed to bring vpon you as touching your exiſtimation or good name and haue ſhewed your ſelf in very déed ſuch a man as in the preamble of your declaration you gladly would be taken to be, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſuch as if you be not alredy: wée verily think that the rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it of all this and ten times as much more will neuer make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou, and therfore can be called no mends vnto you in the tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng: but rather in the honeſt diſtributing therof, which we holde a iuſt and reaſonable Iudgement in all actions of ſuch nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re.</p>
            <p>¶ With that the two parties drew foorth either o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, &amp; cancelled them bothe, and took hands and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eparted home great Fréends ſpite of the Arbitrators and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and ſo ij. Churles were made fréends.</p>
            <p>THis tale béeing ended, <hi>Pierce Plowman</hi> would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éeds ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite with an other tale not vnlike. It chaunce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one day (quoth hée) while I was in my Councellers Cham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er in the Inner Temple: there came a woman dwelling about the Strand, and prayed his councell, and what action ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e might bring againſt an other woman a neighbour of hers, that had ſaid to her in open preſence of diuers of her neighb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs, that ſhe had already twiſe eſcaped the Gallowes. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lawyer aſked of her if ſhe had neuer in her life paſſed by a pair of Gal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowes. She anſwered yes. So haue I doon (quoth h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>) I thank my God, and that ſome time when there haue béen a dozen
<pb facs="tcp:173301:43"/> hanged, and ſo I think haue you (quoth hée). True it is Sir quoth ſhe. Then quoth he, ye cannot recouer for thoſe woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, for they beare good couller of iuſtification, and alſo ſhew that ye haue had better fortune then poſſible many a better mans Childe, and ſo haue I my ſelf alſo. With this anſwere the good woman held her ſelf wel apaid, and went her way con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent.</p>
            <p>THen began my tale. There is dwelling in <hi>Holbourne</hi> (quoth I) and that not very far from the place where I doo lye, a certain man whome I haue noted this long time to be a man of ſtrange affection, for béeing a man of great wealth and therfore the méeter for company, yet if any fréend or neighbour require him to goe with them to the Tauern, to the Ale houſe, to the Theater, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Curtain as they tearm it, or to Paris garden or any ſuch place of expence: he vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſeth, &amp; after their return that willed his company: his maner is to go vnto ſome one of them, deſiring him to tel him truely what hée hath ſpent ſince his going foorth, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing learned at him whether it be a grote or ſixpence, more or leſſe, hée goeth ſtraight vnto a Cofer that hée hath ſtanding ſecretly in his Chamber, which hath a Til, in the which Til there is a little clift, at the which clift hée putteth in aſmuch mony as the partie ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had ſpent, and this til, hée neuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth vntill the end of the yéer, ſo often times hée findeth ther in fortie ſhillings, oft times thrée or foure pound or more and this he taketh and beſtoweth vpon his poore neighbours, and vpon other godly buſines imployeth it.</p>
            <p>And vpon the lid of his Cheſt is written in great Romain letters, take from thy kinde, and giue to the blinde.</p>
            <p>This tale béeing ended, the night ſome what far rumour Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſſe warned vs therof and that it was high time to go to bed, which we were all contented to doo ſauing <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman, who had yet one other tale to tel, and prayed vs to giue him the hearing, which we graunted him, and then hée began.</p>
            <p>¶ There is héer about (quoth <hi>Pierce</hi>) a Gentleman that hath enlarged his rent but not his land (where in many are very expert at this day) &amp; once vpon a time of my being in his
<pb facs="tcp:173301:43"/> houſe there came in a poore tenaunt of his, one that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> béen long tenaunt both to his father and others his Aunc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtors, which poore man pittifully ſaid vnto him as followeth</p>
            <p>Alas Sir (quoth hée) in your Fathers and graundf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers dayes I liued wel and kept at the leaſt twentie Kine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſides Oxen and horſes, and now through your hard dealing with me I am not able to kéep twain.</p>
            <p>Wel quoth the Gentleman thou lieſt, for I haue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to thée: then euer my Father or Grandfather wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for where by thine owne confeſſion in their time thou di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt kéep but twentie Kine: now thou maiſt kéep two hundre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the leaſt, for now (quoth hée) through my fréendſhip thou maiſt be the common Neat hearde, and kéep al the beaſts in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> town.</p>
            <p>And thus our tales béeing all ended: wée required <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of our Hoſteſſe therin, ſhée ſaid that truely in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the Stranger (meaning mée) had tolde the beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ale and wherby ſhée had gotten moſte Example of edifica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion and knowledge, whereby to help and inſtruct both her ſelf and others, and giuing mée great and hartie thanks therfore: ſhée gaue Iudgement that I ſhould break my faſt the next day at the charges of her Huſband and <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman, ſhée ſaid farther that to that man of whome I tolde the tale: ſhée was Detter, if ſhe knew how to doo him good.</p>
            <p>¶ So héer wée ended, and went to bed, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ext day <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman was vp very early, and called mée vp and our Hoſte, (as ſithens I haue learned his maner is alwaies to doo) gathered vs all together with the reſidue of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, mainy, Children and Seruants.</p>
            <p>And hée him ſelf red vnto vs a Chapter of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then wée altogether ſung the fiftéen Pſalme of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and that doon to breakfaſt went, and after break<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt: I my ſelf would néeds pay the whole charges therof, and bid, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the awarde of our Hoſteſſe and their great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to the contrary.)</p>
            <p>And when I would departe: my Hoſte and <hi>Pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi> Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would (whether I would or no) bring mée on my way to <hi>Doncaſter,</hi> and did, and there cauſed mée to haue great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment
<pb facs="tcp:173301:44"/> without a peny charges for one whole day, and then wée took either leaue of other, and departed each of vs toward his owne.</p>
            <p>After which departure, vpon the way as I traueled: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> who ſaith. <hi>I was glad when it was ſaid vnto mee, wee ſhall go into the houſe of the Lord,</hi> which I ſuppoſe be neuer ment by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Inne or hoſterie, where neuertheleſſe I may ſafely ſay I found it. And therfore full true it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Ouid</hi> ſaith, there is oftentimes a good fiſh in a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter where a man would little think. Wée boaſt much of ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and nurture in the South partes of this land, namely in London, and diſpraiſe and diſpiſe the North as rude and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuil, but ſurely for mine owne parte (that am a Southern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and borne in Kent) to ſpeak indifferently for any thing that euer I haue found in all my trauel in both the partes: I cannot ſée nor know why the Northern People ſhould not rather pittie vs then enuie vs concerning either Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Vertue or good maners, for héer I haue ſpoken of the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt kinde of People, wherby it may partly approoue what hope there is of the Gentlemen, merchants and them of the good Townes and Citties, for whoſe ſakes and generally for all others I vndertook to gather and to report this little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and with Gods help and fauour haue doon it as néer accordant to the trueth as I could, neither adding therto nor taking there from, the deſire wherof cauſed mée to take the leſſer Iournies homewarde and to write it by parcells at my Innes leaſt I might haue forgotten it.</p>
            <p>And héerin I proteſt, that I haue neither flattered nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed any man, for my meaning is trueth and the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation therof, and therin is no flattery, for ſurelie if I haue flattered any body: it is mine owne ſelf in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, that where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was perſwaded that pride had vtterly corrupted this whole common welth and had clean ouer ſpred it with his ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neration of all vngodlynes and wickednes wherof all times and ages doo agrée him to be the father: ſithence this Iourney I begin to hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God wil haue mercy vpon vs, and hath and that hée hath reſerued vnto him ſelf a remnaunt as hée did
<pb facs="tcp:173301:44"/> in the time of <hi>Elias,</hi> for whoſe ſakes hée will ſpare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt as hée offered vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> touching <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therfore the intent of this my collection thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: I refer my ſelf to the iudgement of them to whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds it ſhal héerafter come, deſiring their good woord in reco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pence therof, and alſo of my long and weary Iourney wherof this labour was mine only rewarde.</p>
            <p>Beſéeching Almightie God of his great mercie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to graunt vnto the ſame no wurſſe effect then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue ment therin, and that by the Appoſtles councel, we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that wée are but ſtrangers and pilgrimes héer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> earth, and that there after wée may order our liues and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on longing for our owne Cuntrie, content to ſuffer, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to for beare and glad to heare or ſée the thing that may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ée for our edifying, learning and knowledge to bée the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and better welcome into our Cuntrie which is the Heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> whether God for Chriſtes ſake bring vs all Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>✿ <hi>Foelix qui potuit Rerum cognoſcere cauſa</hi>
               </q>
               <q>Who wil ariſe with me againſt the wicked or who wil take my part againſt the euil dooers</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:45"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE APOLOGIE AND</hi> Concluſion of the Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus ended is this ſhorte Collection,</l>
               <l>Rude and vnperfect for his want of ſki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Who ſhould haue giuen it perfection,</l>
               <l>and would, if his might had been to his wil</l>
               <l>Or els if time had therunto ſuffiſed:</l>
               <l>To haue peruſed it and recogniſed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ But for as much as I did fayle of bothe,</l>
               <l>To wit, of Learning and alſo of time:</l>
               <l>And to let dye ſuch matter I was lothe,</l>
               <l>Though I he could it duely enlumine.</l>
               <l>Yet for my God and for my Cuntries ſake:</l>
               <l>Me thought of force I muſt it vndertake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And namely for the woorthy Shire of <hi>Kent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Famous of olde time for humanitie:</l>
               <l>As is to finde in writing auncient,</l>
               <l>Beſides what dayly proof dooth teſtifie.</l>
               <l>Sith I was borne in her me thought of right:</l>
               <l>I ought to bring this matter into light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ So ſtrongly ruleth looue the hart of man,</l>
               <l>Namely that looue which is ſo naturall:</l>
               <l>To doo his Cuntry good in what he can</l>
               <l>That his good hart is to be borne withall.</l>
               <l>For God requeſteth of a man but will:</l>
               <l>Although he want wherwith it to fulfil.</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:173301:45"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
